<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.9.1">Jekyll</generator>
  
  
  <link href="https://dotkay.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="https://dotkay.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" />
  <updated>2021-10-30T17:24:48+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://dotkay.github.io//</id>

  

  
    <subtitle>Learning by teaching</subtitle>
  

  

  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Stories in Charts →</title>
      
      <link href="https://dotkay.github.io/2021/09/22/stories-in-charts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stories in Charts" />
      <published>2021-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://dotkay.github.io/2021/09/22/stories-in-charts</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://dotkay.github.io/2021/09/22/stories-in-charts/">&lt;p&gt;In this post, we will see the most ubiquitous, most useful and also the most easily mis-interpreted data visualization tools - &lt;em&gt;charts&lt;/em&gt;. They come in various forms and they are used to represent different aspects of the underlying data. The key assumption is that the visual representation is easier to interpret quickly than in a tabular format. More often, one kind of story a chart conveys might hide another kind of story a different chart, of the underlying dataset, might have conveyed. It is not uncommon to find that the reader would interpret the chart in a way different from what the writer wanted to convey, in which case it is best for the writer to clarify the message being driven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, let us look at the latest global vaccination data. When you look at the per-capita vaccination rates of different countries, and say you pick the top 50 countries, you would see a chart similar to the following (the chart below is from September, 2021). More specifically, the chart shows the number of fully vaccinated people per hundred of the population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dotkay/data_science/master/plots/people_vax_per_100.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What story does this tell? While per-capita numbers are a way to normalize the data, it crucially depends on the story that one wants to tell. Does this indicate the ease of availability of vaccines? Does it indicate the effectiveness of the healthcare system? Does this indicate the willingness of people to get the vaccine? Or something else?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us look at the absolute numbers for the same data and look at the chart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dotkay/data_science/master/plots/people_vax.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:gray; font-size: 50%; text-align: left;&quot;&gt;
Data regarding fully vaccinated population from China was missing from the dataset and hence it does not show up in the chart. China had the most fully vaccinated population (absolute numbers) in September, 2021.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see a different picture. What story does this tell?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While both of the above charts convey useful information, it is necessary to understand what useful story could be told using the above. For example, the first chart (per-capita) could indicate what percentage of the total population is vaccinated. This could indicate to what extent the spread of the virus or hospitalizations could be contained and that very likely these countries could get out of the pandemic sooner and become safer to travel to. It does not indicate the effectiveness of the healthcare system or the challenges in getting more people vaccinated, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second chart shows the absolute number of people vaccinated in many countries. The difference between the two charts could show the challenges in getting the population vaccinated - it could be geographical as in some countries might be too large posing a logistics challenge, it could be the size of the population - even if enough vaccines are in supply more would be needed to get the entire population vaccinated or it could be a short supply of vaccines - again because of lack of storage or the price or a weak healthcare infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On similar lines, when you look at GDP data and plot the top 50 countries by GDP the chart looks something like the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dotkay/data_science/master/plots/gdp_2018_top_50.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:gray; font-size: 50%; text-align: left;&quot;&gt;
The GDP numbers are from 2018 rather than latest numbers in order to avoid the variations of the effects of the pandemic on GDP.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It shows the wealthiest countries (in terms of GDP). But does the wealth trickle down to every individual? Again, there might be challenges like population, management of funds, etc. Once you look at per-capita numbers one could see how different countries fare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dotkay/data_science/master/plots/gdp_per_capita_2018_top_50.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you look at the GDP growth rate, it tells a different story - the countries that are improving from their past year. Yes, Libya did have 15% GDP growth in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dotkay/data_science/master/plots/gdp_growth_rate_2018.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chart we choose should depend on the story we want to tell. It is imperative to explicitly explain the choice of chart and how it tells the story the writer wants to tell and also the stories it does not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:gray; font-size: 70%; text-align: left;&quot;&gt;
The vaccination data used here is from a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kaggle.com/gpreda/covid-world-vaccination-progress&quot; target=&quot;_self&quot;&gt;Kaggle dataset&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      
        <category term="vaccination" />
      
        <category term="gdp" />
      
        <category term="per-capita" />
      
        <category term="charts" />
      
        <category term="data science" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">In this post, we will see the most ubiquitous, most useful and also the most easily mis-interpreted data visualization tools - charts. They come in various forms and they are used to represent different aspects of the underlying data. The key assumption is that the visual representation is easier to interpret quickly than in a tabular format. More often, one kind of story a chart conveys might hide another kind of story a different chart, of the underlying dataset, might have conveyed. It is not uncommon to find that the reader would interpret the chart in a way different from what the writer wanted to convey, in which case it is best for the writer to clarify the message being driven. For example, let us look at the latest global vaccination data. When you look at the per-capita vaccination rates of different countries, and say you pick the top 50 countries, you would see a chart similar to the following (the chart below is from September, 2021). More specifically, the chart shows the number of fully vaccinated people per hundred of the population. What story does this tell? While per-capita numbers are a way to normalize the data, it crucially depends on the story that one wants to tell. Does this indicate the ease of availability of vaccines? Does it indicate the effectiveness of the healthcare system? Does this indicate the willingness of people to get the vaccine? Or something else? Let us look at the absolute numbers for the same data and look at the chart. Data regarding fully vaccinated population from China was missing from the dataset and hence it does not show up in the chart. China had the most fully vaccinated population (absolute numbers) in September, 2021. We see a different picture. What story does this tell? While both of the above charts convey useful information, it is necessary to understand what useful story could be told using the above. For example, the first chart (per-capita) could indicate what percentage of the total population is vaccinated. This could indicate to what extent the spread of the virus or hospitalizations could be contained and that very likely these countries could get out of the pandemic sooner and become safer to travel to. It does not indicate the effectiveness of the healthcare system or the challenges in getting more people vaccinated, etc. The second chart shows the absolute number of people vaccinated in many countries. The difference between the two charts could show the challenges in getting the population vaccinated - it could be geographical as in some countries might be too large posing a logistics challenge, it could be the size of the population - even if enough vaccines are in supply more would be needed to get the entire population vaccinated or it could be a short supply of vaccines - again because of lack of storage or the price or a weak healthcare infrastructure. On similar lines, when you look at GDP data and plot the top 50 countries by GDP the chart looks something like the following. The GDP numbers are from 2018 rather than latest numbers in order to avoid the variations of the effects of the pandemic on GDP. It shows the wealthiest countries (in terms of GDP). But does the wealth trickle down to every individual? Again, there might be challenges like population, management of funds, etc. Once you look at per-capita numbers one could see how different countries fare. When you look at the GDP growth rate, it tells a different story - the countries that are improving from their past year. Yes, Libya did have 15% GDP growth in 2018. The chart we choose should depend on the story we want to tell. It is imperative to explicitly explain the choice of chart and how it tells the story the writer wants to tell and also the stories it does not. The vaccination data used here is from a Kaggle dataset.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">The Stories of Summer Olympics →</title>
      
      <link href="https://dotkay.github.io/2021/08/16/stories-of-summer-olympics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Stories of Summer Olympics" />
      <published>2021-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://dotkay.github.io/2021/08/16/stories-of-summer-olympics</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://dotkay.github.io/2021/08/16/stories-of-summer-olympics/">&lt;p&gt;This is about the stories of Summer Olympics - not just one story but many stories and not just the recently concluded Tokyo Olympics, but all of the Olympic games since the first one in Athens in 1896. Although the analysis of the medals won by different countries would make the story read like a story medals and achievements statistics, there are other stories hidden within. We will narrate many of those as we do the analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pandas&lt;/code&gt; library to do the data analysis and plotly to create our plots that would tell a visual story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;pandas&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;plotly.express&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;px&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we look at the hosts we see many western powers with Brazil and China (then emerging economies) hosting in 2008 and 2016 respectively. Of course, hosting an Olympics is no small thing - the infrastructure, safety, accessibility, etc. play a huge role and many of these cost money. London seems to be the only city that has hosted Olympics thrice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;total_medals_by_host_city&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;summer_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;groupby&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;([&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'City'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Year'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;as_index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;False&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Medal'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bar&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;total_medals_by_host_city&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'City'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Medal'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;hover_data&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Medal'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Year'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; 
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Medal'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Medals Awarded at Each Venue'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;add_annotation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'London'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1690&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;text&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;London has hosted Olympics thrice...&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;opacity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;1.0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of events in each of the Olympics also seems to be different, as evidenced by the total number of medals awarded during the games. With Paris and London regularly competing for the best European City regularly I believe it is high time Paris got a chance to host the Summer Olympic games, and very glad 2024 Olympics are going to be held in Paris. I also hope more and more emerging economies to be able to host the games. The motivation and interest in sports such events would infuse is invaluable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;igraph&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;border:none;&quot; seamless=&quot;seamless&quot; src=&quot;https://plotly.com/~kkplot/17.embed&quot; height=&quot;525&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we look at the cumulative number of medals won from the start of Summer Olympic games, USA clearly leads. But more important to note here is Russia which was more excellent in sports, science and technology, arts and culture, etc., when it was Soviet Union. Also interesting to note is the presence of an entry &lt;em&gt;Individual athletes&lt;/em&gt; - athletes who chose to compete under the Olympic flag instead of any specific country. This is a political story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;total_medals_by_country&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;summer_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;groupby&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Country'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;as_index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;False&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Medal'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bar&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;total_medals_by_country&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Country'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Medal'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;hover_data&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Medal'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Medal'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Cumulative Number of Medals Won (1896-2021)'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were many instances where athletes who requested to compete independently and were refused - for example, the ones who emigrated from Communist Europe during the cold war, as well as some during the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1976_Olympic_boycott&quot;&gt;1976 Olympic boycott&lt;/a&gt;. The first provisions were made by IOC (International Olympic Committee) during the 1980 Summer Olympics hosted at Moscow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;igraph&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;border:none;&quot; seamless=&quot;seamless&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; src=&quot;https://plotly.com/~kkplot/15.embed&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; width=&quot;1000&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we look at the countries that shine on the top of the medals table regularly the familiar pattern is clear. It is mostly European countries, USA, Australia and more recently China. Although we might have cheered Usain Bolt’s sprints and track and field athletics being one of the most anticipated events of the Summer Olympic games, in terms of total number of medals, many western countries top the table year after year. This also indicates the broad variety and the number of events in the summer games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a political story hidden here, that of the 1980 Summer Olympics. There were only two cities that bid to host the games - Los Angeles and Moscow and eventually Moscow won. If you notice the 1980 Olympics that was hosted by Moscow, Russia seems to be the clear leader in terms of number of medals. Almost always, one expects host country to win several medals, but scoring more medals than the usual competitive powers is always a big achievement. Many nations boycotted the 1980 Olympics, led by the USA to protest against the Soviet-Afghan war. It had the smallest participation - just around 80 countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;top_n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
     &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df&lt;/span&gt; 
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;groupby&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Country&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;agg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;({&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Medal Count&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;sum&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;})&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sort_values&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Medal Count&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ascending&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;False&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;head&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;summer_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;groupby&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;([&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Year'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Country'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Medal'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;reset_index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;columns&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Year'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Country'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Medal'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Medal Count'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bar&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;loc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Country&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;isin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;top_n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)],&lt;/span&gt; 
             &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Year'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Medal Count'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;hover_data&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Country'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Medal Count'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Medal'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Country'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;barmode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'stack'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;color_continuous_scale&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;colors&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sequential&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Viridis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Medal Winners in Olympics'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;iframe id=&quot;igraph&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;border:none;&quot; seamless=&quot;seamless&quot; src=&quot;https://plotly.com/~kkplot/19.embed&quot; height=&quot;800&quot; width=&quot;1000&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are more politics stories in Olympics. The apparent gaps in the plot below makes one wonder what happened those years. The 1916 summer Olympics, to be hosted by Berlin, were cancelled due to World War I, a first cancellation in the 20 year history of Olympics during those days. The 1940 Olympics to be hosted by Tokyo were rescheduled to be hosted by Finland (due to Japan’s invasion of China in 1937) and eventually cancelled due to the outbreak of World War II. Again, the 1944 Summer Olympics to be hosted by London got cancelled due to World War II. The 2020 Olympics hosted by Tokyo was rescheduled to 2021 due to the outbreak of Covid. It took tremendous courage and organization by Japan and the participating countries to put up a great show during the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;igraph&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;border:none;&quot; seamless=&quot;seamless&quot; src=&quot;https://plotly.com/~kkplot/21.embed&quot; height=&quot;800&quot; width=&quot;1000&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df_final&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fillna&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sort_values&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;idcols&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
                         &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;groupby&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;idcols&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:])&lt;/span&gt;
                         &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cumsum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
                         &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;rename&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;columns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Cumulative Total Medals'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;})&lt;/span&gt;
                         &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;reset_index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
                         &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;merge&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dfnoc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;on&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'NOC'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, to finish it off, let us see how the top 25 medal winners (measured as per medals won in 2020)
have fared over the years in terms of total medals won. The rise of China as a major sporting nation is very apparent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;scatter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df_final&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;loc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df_final&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Country&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;isin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;top_n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;25&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)],&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Country&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Cumulative Total Medals&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;log_y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Cumulative Total Medals&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;color_discrete_sequence&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;brown&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;gold&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;silver&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Medal&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;animation_frame&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Year&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;hover_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Country&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;The Olympics Story&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;iframe id=&quot;igraph&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;border:none;&quot; seamless=&quot;seamless&quot; src=&quot;https://plotly.com/~kkplot/24.embed&quot; height=&quot;800&quot; width=&quot;1100&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this short post tells several stories behind the Summer Olympics, I would like to write a future post on the stories behind Paralympics which will would be stories of courge, inspiration and extraordinary commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:gray; font-size: 70%; text-align: left;&quot;&gt;
The data used here is from a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kaggle.com/amirba/olympic-sports-and-medals-18962021&quot; target=&quot;_self&quot;&gt;Kaggle dataset&lt;/a&gt;. This &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kaggle.com/heesoo37/120-years-of-olympic-history-athletes-and-results&quot; target=&quot;_self&quot;&gt;Kaggle dataset&lt;/a&gt; was also used to get NOC (National Olympic Committee) codes of the different countries. Some of the numbers in the dataset does not seem to agree with tables in Wikipedia, nevertheless the differences are not huge to change the story.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      
        <category term="Olympics" />
      
        <category term="medals" />
      
        <category term="data science" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">This is about the stories of Summer Olympics - not just one story but many stories and not just the recently concluded Tokyo Olympics, but all of the Olympic games since the first one in Athens in 1896. Although the analysis of the medals won by different countries would make the story read like a story medals and achievements statistics, there are other stories hidden within. We will narrate many of those as we do the analysis. We will use pandas library to do the data analysis and plotly to create our plots that would tell a visual story. import pandas as pd import plotly.express as px When we look at the hosts we see many western powers with Brazil and China (then emerging economies) hosting in 2008 and 2016 respectively. Of course, hosting an Olympics is no small thing - the infrastructure, safety, accessibility, etc. play a huge role and many of these cost money. London seems to be the only city that has hosted Olympics thrice. total_medals_by_host_city = summer_df.groupby(['City', 'Year'], as_index=False)['Medal'].count() fig = px.bar(total_medals_by_host_city, x='City', y='Medal', hover_data = ['Medal', 'Year'], color='Medal', title='Medals Awarded at Each Venue') fig.add_annotation(x='London', y=1690, text=&quot;London has hosted Olympics thrice...&quot;, ... ... opacity=1.0 ) The number of events in each of the Olympics also seems to be different, as evidenced by the total number of medals awarded during the games. With Paris and London regularly competing for the best European City regularly I believe it is high time Paris got a chance to host the Summer Olympic games, and very glad 2024 Olympics are going to be held in Paris. I also hope more and more emerging economies to be able to host the games. The motivation and interest in sports such events would infuse is invaluable. When we look at the cumulative number of medals won from the start of Summer Olympic games, USA clearly leads. But more important to note here is Russia which was more excellent in sports, science and technology, arts and culture, etc., when it was Soviet Union. Also interesting to note is the presence of an entry Individual athletes - athletes who chose to compete under the Olympic flag instead of any specific country. This is a political story. total_medals_by_country = summer_df.groupby('Country', as_index=False)['Medal'].count() fig = px.bar(total_medals_by_country, x='Country', y='Medal', hover_data = ['Medal'], color='Medal', title='Cumulative Number of Medals Won (1896-2021)') There were many instances where athletes who requested to compete independently and were refused - for example, the ones who emigrated from Communist Europe during the cold war, as well as some during the 1976 Olympic boycott. The first provisions were made by IOC (International Olympic Committee) during the 1980 Summer Olympics hosted at Moscow. When we look at the countries that shine on the top of the medals table regularly the familiar pattern is clear. It is mostly European countries, USA, Australia and more recently China. Although we might have cheered Usain Bolt’s sprints and track and field athletics being one of the most anticipated events of the Summer Olympic games, in terms of total number of medals, many western countries top the table year after year. This also indicates the broad variety and the number of events in the summer games. There is also a political story hidden here, that of the 1980 Summer Olympics. There were only two cities that bid to host the games - Los Angeles and Moscow and eventually Moscow won. If you notice the 1980 Olympics that was hosted by Moscow, Russia seems to be the clear leader in terms of number of medals. Almost always, one expects host country to win several medals, but scoring more medals than the usual competitive powers is always a big achievement. Many nations boycotted the 1980 Olympics, led by the USA to protest against the Soviet-Afghan war. It had the smallest participation - just around 80 countries. def top_n(n): return ( df .groupby(&quot;Country&quot;) .agg({&quot;Medal Count&quot;: &quot;sum&quot;}) .sort_values(&quot;Medal Count&quot;, ascending=False) .head(n) ) df = summer_df.groupby(['Year', 'Country', 'Medal']).size().reset_index() df.columns = ['Year', 'Country', 'Medal', 'Medal Count'] fig = px.bar(df.loc[df[&quot;Country&quot;].isin(top_n(10).index)], x='Year', y='Medal Count', hover_data = ['Country', 'Medal Count', 'Medal'], color='Country', barmode='stack', color_continuous_scale=px.colors.sequential.Viridis, title='Medal Winners in Olympics') There are more politics stories in Olympics. The apparent gaps in the plot below makes one wonder what happened those years. The 1916 summer Olympics, to be hosted by Berlin, were cancelled due to World War I, a first cancellation in the 20 year history of Olympics during those days. The 1940 Olympics to be hosted by Tokyo were rescheduled to be hosted by Finland (due to Japan’s invasion of China in 1937) and eventually cancelled due to the outbreak of World War II. Again, the 1944 Summer Olympics to be hosted by London got cancelled due to World War II. The 2020 Olympics hosted by Tokyo was rescheduled to 2021 due to the outbreak of Covid. It took tremendous courage and organization by Japan and the participating countries to put up a great show during the pandemic. df_final = (df).fillna(0).sort_values(idcols) .groupby(idcols[1:]) .cumsum() .rename(columns={0: 'Cumulative Total Medals'}) .reset_index() .merge(dfnoc, on='NOC') Now, to finish it off, let us see how the top 25 medal winners (measured as per medals won in 2020) have fared over the years in terms of total medals won. The rise of China as a major sporting nation is very apparent. fig = px.scatter( df_final.loc[df_final[&quot;Country&quot;].isin(top_n(25).index)], x=&quot;Country&quot;, y=&quot;Cumulative Total Medals&quot;, log_y=True, size=&quot;Cumulative Total Medals&quot;, color_discrete_sequence=[&quot;brown&quot;,&quot;gold&quot;,&quot;silver&quot;], color=&quot;Medal&quot;, animation_frame=&quot;Year&quot;, hover_name=&quot;Country&quot;, title=&quot;The Olympics Story&quot;, ) While this short post tells several stories behind the Summer Olympics, I would like to write a future post on the stories behind Paralympics which will would be stories of courge, inspiration and extraordinary commitment. The data used here is from a Kaggle dataset. This Kaggle dataset was also used to get NOC (National Olympic Committee) codes of the different countries. Some of the numbers in the dataset does not seem to agree with tables in Wikipedia, nevertheless the differences are not huge to change the story.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">What have people been watching on YouTube? →</title>
      
      <link href="https://dotkay.github.io/2021/06/06/us-youtube-views/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What have people been watching on YouTube?" />
      <published>2021-06-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://dotkay.github.io/2021/06/06/us-youtube-views</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://dotkay.github.io/2021/06/06/us-youtube-views/">&lt;p&gt;For more than 15 months people around the world are mostly staying indoors, those who could are working from home, vacations and other outdoor entertainments have come to a standstill. At the same time, NetFlix, gaming, and other entertainment like TV and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt; must have become more popular - after all, these are the forms of indoor entertainment. I decided to look at what people have been interested within this limited set of entertainment avenues. While I could not find most data, YouTube data was available and regularly updated. I decided to download the dataset that contains YouTube data from August 2020 until early June 2021. Let us see what people (in the U.S.) have been watching on YouTube during this period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yt_us&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;read_csv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'US_youtube_trending_data.csv'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yt_categories&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;read_json&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'US_category_id.json'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yt_us&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dtypes&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The different features in the dataset are (after casting &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;publishedAt&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;trending_date&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;datetime&lt;/code&gt; type):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;video_id                          object
title                             object
publishedAt          datetime64[ns, UTC]
channelId                         object
channelTitle                      object
categoryId                        object
trending_date        datetime64[ns, UTC]
tags                              object
view_count                         int64
likes                              int64
dislikes                           int64
comment_count                      int64
thumbnail_link                    object
comments_disabled                   bool
ratings_disabled                    bool
description                       object
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are different categories of videos in the dataset, and these are the number of videos in each category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dotkay/data_science/master/plots/n_cat_videos.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am surpised by the number of videos in some of the categories or the categorization itself. There is a category on &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;People &amp;amp; Blogs&lt;/code&gt; - I am not sure what it refers to. I do know artists have their own channels and YouTube is a more lively form of a blog, but there is also Music (some of the channels there might also be by music artists). While I try and understand how the different videos are categorized, let us look at some other stats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us find out how many aggregate views each of the different categories has:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cat_view_count_df&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yt_us&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;groupby&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;([&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'categoryId'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'view_count'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;agg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;([&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'sum'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;chart&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;barplot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cat_view_count_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'categoryId'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'view_count'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;palette&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Set2'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;order&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cat_view_count_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sort_values&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'view_count'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ascending&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;False&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;category&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dotkay/data_science/master/plots/nviews_cat_videos.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not surprisingly, Music, Entertainment and Gaming are right at the top. Unfortunately, Education category is way behind. I find YouTube as a wonderful source of education. But may be this is due to Coursera, Udacity, etc. having their own video encoders and decoders and do not have their content on YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us see which were the Top 50 most viewed videos during the time period, in the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# create a new column 'count_max_view' to collect max view_count
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yt_us&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'count_max_view'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yt_us&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;groupby&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;([&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'video_id'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'view_count'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;transform&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;max&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# sort the column so that we can pick out the top 50
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;top50&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yt_us&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yt_us&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'view_count'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yt_us&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'count_max_view'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sort_values&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'count_max_view'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; 
                                                                          &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ascending&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;False&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;head&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;50&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# remove non alpha-numeric characters from the titles
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;top50&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;top50&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;replace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'[^a-zA-Z0-9]'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let us plot the dataset to see which ones are on the top:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;catplot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;top50&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'title'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'view_count'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;kind&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'bar'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;palette&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'muted'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;aspect&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;legend&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;False&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dotkay/data_science/master/plots/top50_yt_videos.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I am fond of Education, I would like to see which YouTube channels have maxinum number of views and check if any of my favourite channels appear in the list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yt_edu&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yt_us&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yt_us&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'categoryId'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Education'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yt_edu&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yt_edu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;groupby&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;([&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'channelTitle'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'view_count'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;agg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;([&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'sum'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;chart&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;barplot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yt_edu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'channelTitle'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'view_count'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;palette&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Set2'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;order&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yt_edu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sort_values&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'view_count'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ascending&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;False&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;channelTitle&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dotkay/data_science/master/plots/yt_edu_views.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see a lot of interesting channels - Khan Academy seems to have just made it to the list. I also see a channel &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/code&gt;. I see lots of interesting channel names and I hope to spend more time exploring those on YouTube very soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kaggle.com/rsrishav/youtube-trending-video-dataset&quot;&gt;YouTube dataset&lt;/a&gt; is also available for other geographies. Someday, I would like to compare how the interests in different geographies differ by comparing YouTube channels’ popularity. It may not be an accurate representation of interests at all, but it should be a fun exercise.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      
        <category term="US" />
      
        <category term="YouTube" />
      
        <category term="Education" />
      
        <category term="Pandemic" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">For more than 15 months people around the world are mostly staying indoors, those who could are working from home, vacations and other outdoor entertainments have come to a standstill. At the same time, NetFlix, gaming, and other entertainment like TV and YouTube must have become more popular - after all, these are the forms of indoor entertainment. I decided to look at what people have been interested within this limited set of entertainment avenues. While I could not find most data, YouTube data was available and regularly updated. I decided to download the dataset that contains YouTube data from August 2020 until early June 2021. Let us see what people (in the U.S.) have been watching on YouTube during this period. yt_us = pd.read_csv('US_youtube_trending_data.csv') yt_categories = pd.read_json('US_category_id.json') yt_us.dtypes The different features in the dataset are (after casting publishedAt and trending_date to datetime type): video_id object title object publishedAt datetime64[ns, UTC] channelId object channelTitle object categoryId object trending_date datetime64[ns, UTC] tags object view_count int64 likes int64 dislikes int64 comment_count int64 thumbnail_link object comments_disabled bool ratings_disabled bool description object There are different categories of videos in the dataset, and these are the number of videos in each category. I am surpised by the number of videos in some of the categories or the categorization itself. There is a category on People &amp;amp; Blogs - I am not sure what it refers to. I do know artists have their own channels and YouTube is a more lively form of a blog, but there is also Music (some of the channels there might also be by music artists). While I try and understand how the different videos are categorized, let us look at some other stats. Let us find out how many aggregate views each of the different categories has: cat_view_count_df = yt_us.groupby(['categoryId'])['view_count'].agg(['sum']) chart = sns.barplot( data=cat_view_count_df, x='categoryId', y='view_count', palette='Set2', order=cat_view_count_df.sort_values('view_count', ascending=False).category ) Not surprisingly, Music, Entertainment and Gaming are right at the top. Unfortunately, Education category is way behind. I find YouTube as a wonderful source of education. But may be this is due to Coursera, Udacity, etc. having their own video encoders and decoders and do not have their content on YouTube. Let us see which were the Top 50 most viewed videos during the time period, in the U.S. # create a new column 'count_max_view' to collect max view_count yt_us['count_max_view'] = yt_us.groupby(['video_id'])['view_count'].transform(max) # sort the column so that we can pick out the top 50 top50 = yt_us[yt_us['view_count'] == yt_us['count_max_view']].sort_values(by=['count_max_view'], ascending=False).head(50) # remove non alpha-numeric characters from the titles top50.title = top50.title.str.replace('[^a-zA-Z0-9]', '') And let us plot the dataset to see which ones are on the top: fig = sns.catplot( data=top50, x='title', y='view_count', kind='bar', palette='muted', aspect=2, legend=False ) Since I am fond of Education, I would like to see which YouTube channels have maxinum number of views and check if any of my favourite channels appear in the list. yt_edu = yt_us[yt_us['categoryId'] == 'Education'] yt_edu = yt_edu.groupby(['channelTitle'])['view_count'].agg(['sum']) chart = sns.barplot( data=yt_edu, x='channelTitle', y='view_count', palette='Set2', order=yt_edu.sort_values('view_count', ascending=False).channelTitle ) I see a lot of interesting channels - Khan Academy seems to have just made it to the list. I also see a channel YouTube. I see lots of interesting channel names and I hope to spend more time exploring those on YouTube very soon. The YouTube dataset is also available for other geographies. Someday, I would like to compare how the interests in different geographies differ by comparing YouTube channels’ popularity. It may not be an accurate representation of interests at all, but it should be a fun exercise.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">U.S. - Job Losses and Recovery →</title>
      
      <link href="https://dotkay.github.io/2021/03/15/us-job-loss-and-recovery/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="U.S. - Job Losses and Recovery" />
      <published>2021-03-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-03-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://dotkay.github.io/2021/03/15/us-job-loss-and-recovery</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://dotkay.github.io/2021/03/15/us-job-loss-and-recovery/">&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://dotkay.github.io/2021/02/21/us-unemployment&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, we saw how many jobs the different states in the U.S. have lost over the years primarily due to trade deficits. In this post, we will visually analyze the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bls.gov/charts/employment-situation/employment-levels-by-industry.htm&quot;&gt;data from BLS&lt;/a&gt; and compare the effects of 2008 recession and the ongoing pandemic on the state of employment in the U.S. across different sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The covid-19 pandemic has definitely wrecked the employment across several sectors of the labor economy and not just the hospitality sector. If we look at the employment numbers for an year starting from January 2020, job losses are evident. We also see the quick recovery (though not to January-2020 levels) in several of the sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;job_cols&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Manufacturing Jobs'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Hospitality Jobs'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Wholesale Jobs'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Retail Jobs'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Transportation Jobs'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Construction Jobs'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Education Health Services Jobs'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Finance Jobs'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Information Jobs'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Mining Jobs'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Other Services Jobs'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Professional Services Jobs'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Utilities Jobs'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;area&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pandemic_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Month&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;job_cols&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
              &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;template&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'simple_white'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;add_annotation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(...)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;show&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;igraph&quot; scrolling=&quot;yes&quot; style=&quot;border:none;&quot; seamless=&quot;seamless&quot; src=&quot;https://plotly.com/~kkplot/10.embed&quot; height=&quot;700&quot; width=&quot;980&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we zoom out in the data set and look at two decades of employment numbers all the way from January 2001 until January 2021, we also see the effect of 2008 recession on employment numbers. We also see how gradual and prolonged the effect of 2008 recession was. The job losses across sectors during the pandemic was sudden and steep and the recovery of numbers was also quick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;area&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;emp_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Month&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;job_cols&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
                   &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;template&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'simple_white'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;add_annotation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(...)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;show&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;igraph&quot; scrolling=&quot;yes&quot; style=&quot;border:none;&quot; seamless=&quot;seamless&quot; src=&quot;https://plotly.com/~kkplot/12.embed&quot; height=&quot;700&quot; width=&quot;980&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can just hope that the recovery from the pandemic continues quicker and reaches early 2020 levels, not only in the U.S. but across the globe. Given that the world is very globalized today than ever before, anyone is healthy and good only when everyone is healthy and good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 70%&quot;&gt;
&lt;i&gt;The tabular BLS data was parsed using BeautifulSoup, and the plots were done using plotly and chart_studio.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      
        <category term="US" />
      
        <category term="labor market" />
      
        <category term="economy" />
      
        <category term="pandemic" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">In a previous post, we saw how many jobs the different states in the U.S. have lost over the years primarily due to trade deficits. In this post, we will visually analyze the data from BLS and compare the effects of 2008 recession and the ongoing pandemic on the state of employment in the U.S. across different sectors. The covid-19 pandemic has definitely wrecked the employment across several sectors of the labor economy and not just the hospitality sector. If we look at the employment numbers for an year starting from January 2020, job losses are evident. We also see the quick recovery (though not to January-2020 levels) in several of the sectors. job_cols = ['Manufacturing Jobs', 'Hospitality Jobs', 'Wholesale Jobs', 'Retail Jobs', 'Transportation Jobs', 'Construction Jobs', 'Education Health Services Jobs', 'Finance Jobs', 'Information Jobs', 'Mining Jobs', 'Other Services Jobs', 'Professional Services Jobs', 'Utilities Jobs'] fig = px.area(pandemic_df, x=&quot;Month&quot;, y=job_cols, template='simple_white') fig.add_annotation(...) ... fig.show() If we zoom out in the data set and look at two decades of employment numbers all the way from January 2001 until January 2021, we also see the effect of 2008 recession on employment numbers. We also see how gradual and prolonged the effect of 2008 recession was. The job losses across sectors during the pandemic was sudden and steep and the recovery of numbers was also quick. fig = px.area(emp_df, x=&quot;Month&quot;, y=job_cols, template='simple_white') fig.add_annotation(...) ... fig.show() We can just hope that the recovery from the pandemic continues quicker and reaches early 2020 levels, not only in the U.S. but across the globe. Given that the world is very globalized today than ever before, anyone is healthy and good only when everyone is healthy and good. The tabular BLS data was parsed using BeautifulSoup, and the plots were done using plotly and chart_studio.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Jobs, Offshoring and Unemployment - US →</title>
      
      <link href="https://dotkay.github.io/2021/02/21/us-unemployment/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jobs, Offshoring and Unemployment - US" />
      <published>2021-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://dotkay.github.io/2021/02/21/us-unemployment</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://dotkay.github.io/2021/02/21/us-unemployment/">&lt;p&gt;With 2020 being one of the worst in recent history, for many reasons fuelled by the pandemic. With many countries being unprepared to handle a pandemic of this size, it also exposed the global supply chain being &lt;a href=&quot;https://dotkay.github.io/2020/04/01/efficiency-vs-flexibility&quot;&gt;highly optimized rather than flexible&lt;/a&gt;. It also exposed the inequality in society - healthcare, job security, income, etc. Many countries had to start manufacturing personal protective equipments (PPE), ventilators, etc. by themselves to serve the local needs rather than rely on the supply chain that got stalled. A couple of decades ago, many of these equipments were manufactured locally but over time, many of those got offshored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this post is not about unemployment due to the pandemic. It is more about loss of U.S. jobs over the period 2001-2017, mostly due to trade deficits, with data from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epi.org/publication/the-china-toll-deepens-growth-in-the-bilateral-trade-deficit-between-2001-and-2017-cost-3-4-million-u-s-jobs-with-losses-in-every-state-and-congressional-district/&quot;&gt;this report&lt;/a&gt; and manufacturing data from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bls.gov/charts/employment-situation/employment-levels-by-industry.htm&quot;&gt;BLS data&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first decade of the century was the worst for U.S. manufacturing jobs. It saw the steepest decline in such jobs, in a very long time. There are two conflicting theories around this - one argues the loss is due to increased automation, while the other attributes the loss to offshoring of such jobs. I could not find the data on rate of automation or increase in manufacturing jobs in other geographies during the time period in order to analyze it analytically. However the loss of jobs, whatever being the root cause, is itself staggering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;plotly.express&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;px&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bar&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;emp_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Month'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Manufacturing Jobs'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;height&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;600&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Manufacturing Jobs'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;labels&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;dict&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;({&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Manufacturing Jobs'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Manufacturing Jobs (in thousands)'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}),&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;template&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'simple_white'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;update_layout&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;autosize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;False&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;700&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;height&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;700&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;show&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;igraph&quot; scrolling=&quot;yes&quot; style=&quot;border:none;&quot; seamless=&quot;seamless&quot; src=&quot;https://plotly.com/~kkplot/6.embed&quot; height=&quot;700&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently, about four decades ago the Bay Area in California was full of orange orchards, and a couple of decades later they all became startups working in electronics and software (Silicon Valley). They were not startups making apps that let teenagers poke and swipe at each other but advanced electronics and software that goes along with it, like routers, modems, semiconductor chips, etc. There were supposedly many small enterprises manufacturing circuit boards and assembling systems for these famous companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An old video of Macintosh Factory in Fremont:
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Dk306ZkNOuc&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But does it mean only the electronics jobs got offshored? Not really. If we look at the data deeper and look at the number of jobs lost state-wise, it gives a more detailed picture. Almost every major state in the U.S. has lost thousands of jobs from 2001-2017, with most of the loss happening between 2001-2009. Many other states would have seen loss of jobs in other industries like automobiles and steel included.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bar&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'State'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Jobs Lost'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;height&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;600&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'% Jobs Lost'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
             &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;labels&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;dict&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;({&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Jobs Lost'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Jobs Lost (in thousands)'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;show&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;igraph&quot; scrolling=&quot;yes&quot; style=&quot;border:none;&quot; seamless=&quot;seamless&quot; src=&quot;https://plotly.com/~kkplot/1.embed&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; width=&quot;980&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we look even deeper into the data, we can see how many jobs were lost in each state’s congressional districts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bar&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Total Jobs'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'State'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'% Jobs Lost'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
             &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;labels&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;dict&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;({&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'State'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'States and Congressional Districts'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}),&lt;/span&gt;
             &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;hover_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Congressional District'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;show&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;igraph&quot; scrolling=&quot;yes&quot; style=&quot;border:none;&quot; seamless=&quot;seamless&quot; src=&quot;https://plotly.com/~kkplot/4.embed&quot; height=&quot;870&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I find reliable data on rate of automation and manufacturing jobs gained in other geographies, analysis of that data would help in putting the pieces together. While I am not against offshoring, I am all for a more flexible supply chain, rather than a super-optimized supply chain that would get disrupted affecting the lives and livelihoods of several people, as we witnessed last year when medical devices and PPE supply chain got disrupted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While many jobs have been offshored causing large scale unemployment, there is still hope for reskilling of workers and creating new jobs that would drive the economy the next two decades - like solar panels, &lt;a href=&quot;https://dotkay.github.io/2020/09/13/electric-batteries&quot;&gt;electric batteries&lt;/a&gt;, recycling of batteries, advanced technologies for water, air purification, education and healthcare, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 70%&quot;&gt;
&lt;i&gt;The tabular data from EPI report was parsed using BeautifulSoup, and the plots were done using plotly and chart_studio.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      
        <category term="US" />
      
        <category term="labor market" />
      
        <category term="economy" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">With 2020 being one of the worst in recent history, for many reasons fuelled by the pandemic. With many countries being unprepared to handle a pandemic of this size, it also exposed the global supply chain being highly optimized rather than flexible. It also exposed the inequality in society - healthcare, job security, income, etc. Many countries had to start manufacturing personal protective equipments (PPE), ventilators, etc. by themselves to serve the local needs rather than rely on the supply chain that got stalled. A couple of decades ago, many of these equipments were manufactured locally but over time, many of those got offshored. However, this post is not about unemployment due to the pandemic. It is more about loss of U.S. jobs over the period 2001-2017, mostly due to trade deficits, with data from this report and manufacturing data from BLS data. The first decade of the century was the worst for U.S. manufacturing jobs. It saw the steepest decline in such jobs, in a very long time. There are two conflicting theories around this - one argues the loss is due to increased automation, while the other attributes the loss to offshoring of such jobs. I could not find the data on rate of automation or increase in manufacturing jobs in other geographies during the time period in order to analyze it analytically. However the loss of jobs, whatever being the root cause, is itself staggering. import plotly.express as px fig = px.bar(emp_df[:100], x='Month', y='Manufacturing Jobs', height=600, color='Manufacturing Jobs', labels=dict({'Manufacturing Jobs':'Manufacturing Jobs (in thousands)'}), template='simple_white') fig.update_layout( autosize=False, width=700, height=700 ) fig.show() Apparently, about four decades ago the Bay Area in California was full of orange orchards, and a couple of decades later they all became startups working in electronics and software (Silicon Valley). They were not startups making apps that let teenagers poke and swipe at each other but advanced electronics and software that goes along with it, like routers, modems, semiconductor chips, etc. There were supposedly many small enterprises manufacturing circuit boards and assembling systems for these famous companies. An old video of Macintosh Factory in Fremont: But does it mean only the electronics jobs got offshored? Not really. If we look at the data deeper and look at the number of jobs lost state-wise, it gives a more detailed picture. Almost every major state in the U.S. has lost thousands of jobs from 2001-2017, with most of the loss happening between 2001-2009. Many other states would have seen loss of jobs in other industries like automobiles and steel included. fig = px.bar(df, x='State', y='Jobs Lost', height=600, color='% Jobs Lost', labels=dict({'Jobs Lost':'Jobs Lost (in thousands)'})) fig.show() If we look even deeper into the data, we can see how many jobs were lost in each state’s congressional districts. fig = px.bar(df, x='Total Jobs', y='State', color='% Jobs Lost', labels=dict({'State':'States and Congressional Districts'}), hover_name='Congressional District') fig.show() When I find reliable data on rate of automation and manufacturing jobs gained in other geographies, analysis of that data would help in putting the pieces together. While I am not against offshoring, I am all for a more flexible supply chain, rather than a super-optimized supply chain that would get disrupted affecting the lives and livelihoods of several people, as we witnessed last year when medical devices and PPE supply chain got disrupted. While many jobs have been offshored causing large scale unemployment, there is still hope for reskilling of workers and creating new jobs that would drive the economy the next two decades - like solar panels, electric batteries, recycling of batteries, advanced technologies for water, air purification, education and healthcare, etc. The tabular data from EPI report was parsed using BeautifulSoup, and the plots were done using plotly and chart_studio.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Is it GameStop vs Hedge Funds or GameStop vs Streaming? →</title>
      
      <link href="https://dotkay.github.io/2021/01/19/gme-wall-street/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is it GameStop vs Hedge Funds or GameStop vs Streaming?" />
      <published>2021-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://dotkay.github.io/2021/01/19/gme-wall-street</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://dotkay.github.io/2021/01/19/gme-wall-street/">&lt;p&gt;Everyone knows GameStop now, and its ticker symbol too - gamers, non-gamers, traders, non-traders, all alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GameStop is a chain of retail stores that sells game merchandise, equipment and at one point (when games were sold on CDs) games. Retail is moving online and if the product is software, it has already moved. I can’t recollect the last time I saw Windows OS or Office sold in a CD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hedge funds apparently make money by betting on such companies - borrow money or company shares from some lender promising to repay and in the mean time, bet on the downside of the company, wait for the price to crash, buy the stock (for cheap) and give it back to the lender (pocketing the difference). I am not sure how they pick companies to bet on. However, late last year and early January, GameStop was the candidate. In order to revolt againt this, some online enthusiasts mobilized themselves to buy options on this stock, thereby increasing the stock price (‘stock price’ not ‘company value’) that would hurt the Hedge funds’ intentions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us look at some data to see if Hedge funds are the real detterants to GameStop’s future or if there are other factors - like streaming. It was not just GameStop (GME), but also Nokia (NOK), AMC and Blackberry (BB) that went through this early January, but GameStop had the biggest change. Just to show the trend in these stocks (GameStop removed from the plot below as the change in GME was too high that the other trends wouldn’t show up well). Notice how the overall trend in stock prices have been over the last few years and how it changed towards the end of 2020 and early 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;amc_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Date'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;amc_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Adj Close'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;label&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'AMC'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;nok_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Date'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;nok_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Adj Close'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;label&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'NOK'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bb_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Date'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bb_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Adj Close'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;label&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'BB'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dotkay/data_science/master/plots/amc_nok_bb.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to see what (game) streaming industry is like, I started looking for data on this - number of subscribers, streamers, etc. I found &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitchtracker.com/statistics&quot;&gt;Twitchtracker&lt;/a&gt; that tracks statistics on Twitch. Since Twitch’s data was easiest to get and well organized, I decided to look at just Twitch data (number of concurrent viewers) and plot it alongside GameStop stock price over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ax1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;subplots&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ax2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ax1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;twinx&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;line1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ax1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;gme_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'month'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;gme_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Adj Close'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'blue'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;line2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ax2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;twitch_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'month'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;twitch_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'avg_concurrent_viewers'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'green'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;show&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dotkay/data_science/master/plots/gme_vs_twitch.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of Twitch channels also keep increasing along with the number of viewers and this trend is only likely to continue during these pandemic times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;scatter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'avg_concurrent_viewers'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;               
                     &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'avg_concurrent_channels'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
                     &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'time_watched'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;show&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dotkay/data_science/master/plots/twitch_data.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2020/3/20/21188799/gamestop-california-store-closures-indefinite-coronavirus&quot;&gt;many retail stores like GameStop’s were hit hard&lt;/a&gt; during the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone can infer the trend in the industry. Hedge funds are disliked for several reasons, some of them valid. But the future of gaming is online and if GameStop were to survive, it has to build that future than anchor itself in its glorious past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 70%&quot;&gt;
&lt;i&gt;The data from Twitchtracker was parsed using BeautifulSoup, and the plots were done using matplotlib, seaborn and plotly.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      
        <category term="GameStop" />
      
        <category term="markets" />
      
        <category term="short selling" />
      
        <category term="wall street" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">Everyone knows GameStop now, and its ticker symbol too - gamers, non-gamers, traders, non-traders, all alike. GameStop is a chain of retail stores that sells game merchandise, equipment and at one point (when games were sold on CDs) games. Retail is moving online and if the product is software, it has already moved. I can’t recollect the last time I saw Windows OS or Office sold in a CD. Hedge funds apparently make money by betting on such companies - borrow money or company shares from some lender promising to repay and in the mean time, bet on the downside of the company, wait for the price to crash, buy the stock (for cheap) and give it back to the lender (pocketing the difference). I am not sure how they pick companies to bet on. However, late last year and early January, GameStop was the candidate. In order to revolt againt this, some online enthusiasts mobilized themselves to buy options on this stock, thereby increasing the stock price (‘stock price’ not ‘company value’) that would hurt the Hedge funds’ intentions. Let us look at some data to see if Hedge funds are the real detterants to GameStop’s future or if there are other factors - like streaming. It was not just GameStop (GME), but also Nokia (NOK), AMC and Blackberry (BB) that went through this early January, but GameStop had the biggest change. Just to show the trend in these stocks (GameStop removed from the plot below as the change in GME was too high that the other trends wouldn’t show up well). Notice how the overall trend in stock prices have been over the last few years and how it changed towards the end of 2020 and early 2021. ... plt.plot(amc_df['Date'], amc_df['Adj Close'], label='AMC') plt.plot(nok_df['Date'], nok_df['Adj Close'], label='NOK') plt.plot(bb_df['Date'], bb_df['Adj Close'], label='BB') plt.plot() ... In order to see what (game) streaming industry is like, I started looking for data on this - number of subscribers, streamers, etc. I found Twitchtracker that tracks statistics on Twitch. Since Twitch’s data was easiest to get and well organized, I decided to look at just Twitch data (number of concurrent viewers) and plot it alongside GameStop stock price over the years. fig, ax1 = plt.subplots() ax2 = ax1.twinx() line1, = ax1.plot(gme_df['month'], gme_df['Adj Close'], color='blue') line2, = ax2.plot(twitch_df['month'], twitch_df['avg_concurrent_viewers']//1000, color='green') ... plt.show() The number of Twitch channels also keep increasing along with the number of viewers and this trend is only likely to continue during these pandemic times. fig = px.scatter(df, x='avg_concurrent_viewers', y='avg_concurrent_channels', size='time_watched') fig.show() On the other hand many retail stores like GameStop’s were hit hard during the pandemic. Everyone can infer the trend in the industry. Hedge funds are disliked for several reasons, some of them valid. But the future of gaming is online and if GameStop were to survive, it has to build that future than anchor itself in its glorious past. The data from Twitchtracker was parsed using BeautifulSoup, and the plots were done using matplotlib, seaborn and plotly.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">TSLA joins S&amp;amp;P 500 →</title>
      
      <link href="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/12/24/tsla-spy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TSLA joins S&amp;P 500" />
      <published>2020-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://dotkay.github.io/2020/12/24/tsla-spy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/12/24/tsla-spy/">&lt;p&gt;A week ago Tesla Motors (TSLA) joined the S&amp;amp;P 500 Index - the stock market index that keeps track of the performance of 500 largest companies listed in stock markets in the US. Overall TSLA has been very volatile - many argue that the volatility (risk) indicates the opportunies for Tesla. Now that we are towards the end of the year, a pandemic year, let’s see how the S&amp;amp;P 500 performed and how Tesla performed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in terms of the value of TSLA stock and S&amp;amp;P 500 Index, this is how they fared during this year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dotkay/data_science/master/plots/tsla_gspc_2020.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tsla_df&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pdr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;get_data_yahoo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;TSLA&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
                              &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;start&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;2010-07-01&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
                              &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;2020-12-20&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
                              &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;interval&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;wk&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;snp_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Date'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;snp_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Adj Close'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;label&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'S&amp;amp;P'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tsla_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Date'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tsla_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Adj Close'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;label&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'TSLA'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;xlabel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Date'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ylabel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Market Value'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;                       
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the data was collected using pandas_datareader and the plots done using seaborn library.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      
        <category term="energy" />
      
        <category term="electric" />
      
        <category term="S&amp;P 500" />
      
        <category term="TSLA" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">A week ago Tesla Motors (TSLA) joined the S&amp;amp;P 500 Index - the stock market index that keeps track of the performance of 500 largest companies listed in stock markets in the US. Overall TSLA has been very volatile - many argue that the volatility (risk) indicates the opportunies for Tesla. Now that we are towards the end of the year, a pandemic year, let’s see how the S&amp;amp;P 500 performed and how Tesla performed. And in terms of the value of TSLA stock and S&amp;amp;P 500 Index, this is how they fared during this year: tsla_df = pdr.get_data_yahoo(&quot;TSLA&quot;, start=&quot;2010-07-01&quot;, end=&quot;2020-12-20&quot;, interval=&quot;wk&quot;) ... ... plt.plot(snp_df['Date'], snp_df['Adj Close'],label='S&amp;amp;P') plt.plot(tsla_df['Date'], tsla_df['Adj Close'], label='TSLA') plt.xlabel('Date') plt.ylabel('Market Value') ... ... All the data was collected using pandas_datareader and the plots done using seaborn library.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Our Sense of Self →</title>
      
      <link href="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/10/10/sense-of-self/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our Sense of Self" />
      <published>2020-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://dotkay.github.io/2020/10/10/sense-of-self</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/10/10/sense-of-self/">&lt;p&gt;We perceive our sense of self as an amalgamation of the different sensory inputs - visual, tactile, locomotive, etc., that our brain processes and interprets. Or in other words, our sense of self is an interpretation made for us by our brain (mind) after processing several inputs. In olden days philosophers who tried to understand one’s true self found it difficult to reason about the interpretation of sense of self - are we really who we are? or are we manifestations of our mind’s interpretation of several inputs? This is a fascinating topic and lately neuroscience research is trying to understand which parts of the brain are processing and how our brain creates such interpretations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Man-Who-Wasnt-There-Investigations/dp/0525954198&quot;&gt;The Man Who Wasn’t There&lt;/a&gt;, journalist Anil Ananthaswamy takes us through the neuroscience research on this topic. The main message of this book is that our sense of self is an interpretation of several inputs which are beyond just sensory inputs but our own physical body and society play a vital role. And in this age where Computer Scientists are working on Deep Learning as well as trying to understand the neurological pathways in order to build systems that mimic the human decision making apparatus, while that apparatus itself is not completely understood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What fascinates me about this study is how the mind’s computation of sense of self can be influenced (or cheated) by changing the mapping (think of it as lookup table entries) the mind preserves for different sensory and other inputs. In many cases, what we feel and believe our sense of self is, is just an interpretation (an entry in the table) that is fetched given the inputs. We can influence such inputs to pick up a different entry that would alter our sense of self. There is also a classic neuroscience experiment from the 90s that demonstrates how the mapping in our brain, representing our physical sense of self, can be altered within minutes. You can take a look at an example experiment below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ASM12lpDDy0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am intrigued about the possibility of changing our emotional sense of self and if it could be done non-invasively using technology. Such a possibility would be a big boost to curing several mental disorders just by altering the mapping in the mind, when we know how the mapping is created, where it is stored and how it is interpreted. Also, one needs to be aware of ramifications of this - can such mappings be altered by say adversarial inputs - visual or societal - in the form of social media posts or news articles. We might be destroying our own sense of self by letting our mind interpret the inputs that we consume, without us realizing the end result - thinking we are who our mind interprets (influenced interpretation/self) rather than who we really are (actual self).&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      
        <category term="mind" />
      
        <category term="psychology" />
      
        <category term="philosophy" />
      
        <category term="neuroscience" />
      
        <category term="brain" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">We perceive our sense of self as an amalgamation of the different sensory inputs - visual, tactile, locomotive, etc., that our brain processes and interprets. Or in other words, our sense of self is an interpretation made for us by our brain (mind) after processing several inputs. In olden days philosophers who tried to understand one’s true self found it difficult to reason about the interpretation of sense of self - are we really who we are? or are we manifestations of our mind’s interpretation of several inputs? This is a fascinating topic and lately neuroscience research is trying to understand which parts of the brain are processing and how our brain creates such interpretations. In his book, The Man Who Wasn’t There, journalist Anil Ananthaswamy takes us through the neuroscience research on this topic. The main message of this book is that our sense of self is an interpretation of several inputs which are beyond just sensory inputs but our own physical body and society play a vital role. And in this age where Computer Scientists are working on Deep Learning as well as trying to understand the neurological pathways in order to build systems that mimic the human decision making apparatus, while that apparatus itself is not completely understood. What fascinates me about this study is how the mind’s computation of sense of self can be influenced (or cheated) by changing the mapping (think of it as lookup table entries) the mind preserves for different sensory and other inputs. In many cases, what we feel and believe our sense of self is, is just an interpretation (an entry in the table) that is fetched given the inputs. We can influence such inputs to pick up a different entry that would alter our sense of self. There is also a classic neuroscience experiment from the 90s that demonstrates how the mapping in our brain, representing our physical sense of self, can be altered within minutes. You can take a look at an example experiment below: I am intrigued about the possibility of changing our emotional sense of self and if it could be done non-invasively using technology. Such a possibility would be a big boost to curing several mental disorders just by altering the mapping in the mind, when we know how the mapping is created, where it is stored and how it is interpreted. Also, one needs to be aware of ramifications of this - can such mappings be altered by say adversarial inputs - visual or societal - in the form of social media posts or news articles. We might be destroying our own sense of self by letting our mind interpret the inputs that we consume, without us realizing the end result - thinking we are who our mind interprets (influenced interpretation/self) rather than who we really are (actual self).</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Electric Batteries and Supply Chain Economics →</title>
      
      <link href="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/09/13/electric-batteries/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Electric Batteries and Supply Chain Economics" />
      <published>2020-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://dotkay.github.io/2020/09/13/electric-batteries</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/09/13/electric-batteries/">&lt;p&gt;One of the many issues the global pandemic has exposed is the (mostly) single point of failure in global supply chain systems. Over the last couple of decades global corporations optimized their supply chain to such an extent that it became far from flexible, while being extremely optimized. While the supply chain disruptions in today’s products - from face masks to medical equipments got exposed, this post is about the future supply chain challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With many countries rallying towards fighting climate change, electric vehicles are at the forefront of that fight. With the cost per kilowatt-hour touching $100/kWhr or even less, electric vehicles would not only make economic sense but also reduce the total cost of ownership drastically. While American companies like Tesla are at the head of the pack in innovation and execution, the components for uninterrupted production as well as security lie elsewhere - the supply chain for electric car batteries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Benchmark’s Simon Mores says there are two ways of reducing cost of Li-ion batteries:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Controlling the supply of raw materials that go into batteries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changing how batteries are made (scale)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the prices of raw materials were at all time high, companies like Tesla maintain lead by controlling the manufacturing process - “the scale” as 25-40% of the cost of an electric vehicle can be attributed to the cost of the battery. That is where Gigafactories become interesting and so does controlling the supply chain. But so far, American auto companies, to a large extent, have only been assembling the components that constitute the battery. There is a lot of effort that goes into a battery before this final assembly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us break this apart looking at the value chain of electric battery manufacturing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dotkay/tmp/main/misc/ev_bat_value_chain.PNG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If one were to superimpose the geographies that control different parts of the value chain, one could immediately see the premonitions of future supply chain challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dotkay/tmp/main/misc/ev_bat_value_chain_geo.PNG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 50% of every one of the raw materials is dependent on one geography, which is a recipe for future disruptions. As Benchmark’s Vivas Kumar points out, the only part of the value chain that can’t be moved around are the mines themselves. Every other part of the value chain can be located in different parts of the globe. Most of the early stages of the value chain like Cathode, cell manufacturing, etc. are controlled predominantly by specific geographies that would be a supply chain and security risk when electric vehicles become like mobile phones. A wise thing for such an industry like Auto to do is to shore up the different components so that the critical component (battery) supply is not disrupted in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One has to wait and see if the electric battery supply chain gets reshored and does not become another disruption waiting to happen or if short term optimization goals will lead to long-term disasters, just as it is happening in semiconductors and electronics.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      
        <category term="electric battery" />
      
        <category term="Li" />
      
        <category term="Manufacturing" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">One of the many issues the global pandemic has exposed is the (mostly) single point of failure in global supply chain systems. Over the last couple of decades global corporations optimized their supply chain to such an extent that it became far from flexible, while being extremely optimized. While the supply chain disruptions in today’s products - from face masks to medical equipments got exposed, this post is about the future supply chain challenges. With many countries rallying towards fighting climate change, electric vehicles are at the forefront of that fight. With the cost per kilowatt-hour touching $100/kWhr or even less, electric vehicles would not only make economic sense but also reduce the total cost of ownership drastically. While American companies like Tesla are at the head of the pack in innovation and execution, the components for uninterrupted production as well as security lie elsewhere - the supply chain for electric car batteries. As Benchmark’s Simon Mores says there are two ways of reducing cost of Li-ion batteries: Controlling the supply of raw materials that go into batteries Changing how batteries are made (scale) While the prices of raw materials were at all time high, companies like Tesla maintain lead by controlling the manufacturing process - “the scale” as 25-40% of the cost of an electric vehicle can be attributed to the cost of the battery. That is where Gigafactories become interesting and so does controlling the supply chain. But so far, American auto companies, to a large extent, have only been assembling the components that constitute the battery. There is a lot of effort that goes into a battery before this final assembly. Let us break this apart looking at the value chain of electric battery manufacturing: If one were to superimpose the geographies that control different parts of the value chain, one could immediately see the premonitions of future supply chain challenges. More than 50% of every one of the raw materials is dependent on one geography, which is a recipe for future disruptions. As Benchmark’s Vivas Kumar points out, the only part of the value chain that can’t be moved around are the mines themselves. Every other part of the value chain can be located in different parts of the globe. Most of the early stages of the value chain like Cathode, cell manufacturing, etc. are controlled predominantly by specific geographies that would be a supply chain and security risk when electric vehicles become like mobile phones. A wise thing for such an industry like Auto to do is to shore up the different components so that the critical component (battery) supply is not disrupted in the future. One has to wait and see if the electric battery supply chain gets reshored and does not become another disruption waiting to happen or if short term optimization goals will lead to long-term disasters, just as it is happening in semiconductors and electronics.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Technologies in Online Education →</title>
      
      <link href="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/07/01/online-education-part-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Technologies in Online Education" />
      <published>2020-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://dotkay.github.io/2020/07/01/online-education-part-2</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/07/01/online-education-part-2/">&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://dotkay.github.io/2020/05/25/online-education-part-1&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; we saw the challenges in accessing quality education digitally. In this post, we will look at some of the disparate pieces of technology that could work together to make online education less expensive, more efficient and hopefully more accessible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a 45000 ft. view, online education is just about a video playing in a TV or a computer browser, much like any TV program or YouTube or Vimeo video would. But there is a lot more to it as you go down into the details. Even in its simplest form (i.e. no authentication, account validation, etc.,) most of them contain video and audio streams, which itself is the first bottleneck for places which have poor internet bandwidths, if at all internet exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the very first technical problem is to address bandwidth the way several streaming services address them - by encoding them in different qualities and formats, cache them in CDNs or edge networks efficiently, predict their access patterns and serve them efficiently. This alone may not be enough - for most of the world the only access to internet may be through a not-so-good mobile data network which might still be prohibitively expensive to stream high quality videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the second problem: video quality. Since most educational videos, unlike action movie frames, are to a large extent relatively slow moving and not lots of dynamic pixel changes, AI techniques used for &lt;em&gt;Super Resolution&lt;/em&gt; can be employed to create a higher resolution content on device even if the incoming videos from the nearest edge network are low resolution ones. But what about the device - does it need to be one with an expensive GPU attached to it? Not really.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That brings us to the third problem: device specifications. The most desired characteristic of the device would be longer battery life and quick recharge capability. Since most education content (the content itself) is generated before the class (the event) and the content is just delivered live, modest processing power should be enough to do the inference side of super resolution. Chromebooks and android devices are a first step in this direction, but a main area of improvement would also be how long the device lasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most students are visual learners but most educational content is dry. One could use components of game development engines to develop tools for teachers so that they can create interesting animations and content for their class without having to learn and program using game engines. We have been living with Powerpoint for content creation for more than three decades and may be it is time to add more interesting content creation capabilities to Powerpoint or move to an application that provides such capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most digital content is created in English, Mandarin and Spanish while there are many other languages and many research suggest that one’s first language is the best medium for early education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While translating languages from one to another automatically is not effective as of today, future AI technologies would hopefully be able to bridge this gap as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Students with special needs would require more help both from technology and human beings in order to enjoy and benefit from online education. If technology can leave more time for teachers they could invest that gained time on students with special needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several other problems where technology could play a role. One could create authentication mechanisms for examinations and awarding certificate of completion of courses. Zoom like video conferencing technologies could be used both for delivering the content as well as break rooms for further guidance. Automated algorithms could test basics of the students’ knowledge of a topic and have progressively challenging exercises, rather than a one-size-fits-all teaching and evaluation model that is currently in place. A content created by one teacher or school can be securely shared with another school, optimizing the time and effort put in for content creation. The content itself could be stored in cloud storage and personalization algorithms could recommend what other YouTube or other content would be helpful in understanding the concepts in a specific topic, instead of the students straying all over the web looking for explanations to fortify their understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are lots of ways things could improve. But in reality, most such softwares are fragmented. One might use a chromebook while the slides sent out by the teacher would be in powerpoint format, one video would be on YouTube, one would be lying as an mpeg file in a shared folder. One would use zoom and the other Webex or Teams and there is no way these applications are play well together. Further, the current techniques for first party and third party integrations of content creation and marketing might bump up content rich in marketing dollars while relatively punishing content rich in content. Nevertheless, technology would play a huge role not only in school education but also enterprise reskilling (education technology would be an enterprise product as well) and the one who wins would be the one who builds the strongest platform combining the disparate technologies listed above, and some more.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      
        <category term="online" />
      
        <category term="education" />
      
        <category term="technology" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">In a previous post we saw the challenges in accessing quality education digitally. In this post, we will look at some of the disparate pieces of technology that could work together to make online education less expensive, more efficient and hopefully more accessible. From a 45000 ft. view, online education is just about a video playing in a TV or a computer browser, much like any TV program or YouTube or Vimeo video would. But there is a lot more to it as you go down into the details. Even in its simplest form (i.e. no authentication, account validation, etc.,) most of them contain video and audio streams, which itself is the first bottleneck for places which have poor internet bandwidths, if at all internet exists. So, the very first technical problem is to address bandwidth the way several streaming services address them - by encoding them in different qualities and formats, cache them in CDNs or edge networks efficiently, predict their access patterns and serve them efficiently. This alone may not be enough - for most of the world the only access to internet may be through a not-so-good mobile data network which might still be prohibitively expensive to stream high quality videos. This brings us to the second problem: video quality. Since most educational videos, unlike action movie frames, are to a large extent relatively slow moving and not lots of dynamic pixel changes, AI techniques used for Super Resolution can be employed to create a higher resolution content on device even if the incoming videos from the nearest edge network are low resolution ones. But what about the device - does it need to be one with an expensive GPU attached to it? Not really. That brings us to the third problem: device specifications. The most desired characteristic of the device would be longer battery life and quick recharge capability. Since most education content (the content itself) is generated before the class (the event) and the content is just delivered live, modest processing power should be enough to do the inference side of super resolution. Chromebooks and android devices are a first step in this direction, but a main area of improvement would also be how long the device lasts. Most students are visual learners but most educational content is dry. One could use components of game development engines to develop tools for teachers so that they can create interesting animations and content for their class without having to learn and program using game engines. We have been living with Powerpoint for content creation for more than three decades and may be it is time to add more interesting content creation capabilities to Powerpoint or move to an application that provides such capabilities. Most digital content is created in English, Mandarin and Spanish while there are many other languages and many research suggest that one’s first language is the best medium for early education. While translating languages from one to another automatically is not effective as of today, future AI technologies would hopefully be able to bridge this gap as well. Students with special needs would require more help both from technology and human beings in order to enjoy and benefit from online education. If technology can leave more time for teachers they could invest that gained time on students with special needs. There are several other problems where technology could play a role. One could create authentication mechanisms for examinations and awarding certificate of completion of courses. Zoom like video conferencing technologies could be used both for delivering the content as well as break rooms for further guidance. Automated algorithms could test basics of the students’ knowledge of a topic and have progressively challenging exercises, rather than a one-size-fits-all teaching and evaluation model that is currently in place. A content created by one teacher or school can be securely shared with another school, optimizing the time and effort put in for content creation. The content itself could be stored in cloud storage and personalization algorithms could recommend what other YouTube or other content would be helpful in understanding the concepts in a specific topic, instead of the students straying all over the web looking for explanations to fortify their understanding. There are lots of ways things could improve. But in reality, most such softwares are fragmented. One might use a chromebook while the slides sent out by the teacher would be in powerpoint format, one video would be on YouTube, one would be lying as an mpeg file in a shared folder. One would use zoom and the other Webex or Teams and there is no way these applications are play well together. Further, the current techniques for first party and third party integrations of content creation and marketing might bump up content rich in marketing dollars while relatively punishing content rich in content. Nevertheless, technology would play a huge role not only in school education but also enterprise reskilling (education technology would be an enterprise product as well) and the one who wins would be the one who builds the strongest platform combining the disparate technologies listed above, and some more.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Global Trends in Electric Vehicles →</title>
      
      <link href="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/06/06/evs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Global Trends in Electric Vehicles" />
      <published>2020-06-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://dotkay.github.io/2020/06/06/evs</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/06/06/evs/">&lt;p&gt;In an &lt;a href=&quot;https://dotkay.github.io/2020/06/01/covid-vs-coal/&quot;&gt;earlier post&lt;/a&gt;, we learnt something that we do not see everyday, even if we work in a coal mine, as the variety of energy and the consumption end points blind us from looking at the full picture. Today, we will look at some trends that we see all around us, all the time - Electric vehicles (EVs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most of us, an &lt;em&gt;electric car&lt;/em&gt; immediately reminds us of Tesla - the innovative American automobile manufacturer that is to become the world’s most valuable automobile company very soon. Tesla is also the company that created an electric car revolution. Tesla’s success, in many ways, drove other automakers to accelerate their offering of all-electric products. We saw that the transition was not overnight. Many built hybrid vehicles (HEV), range-extended electric vehicles, plug-in hybrid vehicles (PHEV), before building all electric, or battery electric vehicles (BEV). However, if one is to guess which country on the planet has the most number of electric cars it would most likely be the US or EU, because of Tesla and the likes of VW or BMW (both of which make electric cars). Let’s see how the actual answer unfolds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iea.org/reports/global-ev-outlook-2020&quot;&gt;IEA’s global outlook&lt;/a&gt; and data show some impressive numbers. To quote from their report,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Only about 17 000 electric cars were on the world’s roads in 2010. By 2019, that number had swelled to 7.2 million, 47% of which were in The People’s Republic of China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/energy/evs.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;EVs in the world&quot; class=&quot;img=responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, despite purchase subsidies for electric cars were cut in many geographies (like tax credits in the US) and the resulting drop in electric car sales, the total number electric vehicles in China, EU and the US are still very impressive - 2.58 million BEVs in China compared to 0.88 million BEVs in the US and 0.97 million BEVs in the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One would start thinking what other industries are getting transformed along with the transformation of automotive industry. The implications of this transformation are huge touching several industries from service industry, retail and insurance. The analysis of the transformation itself would give fascninating insights. That would be the topic of a future post.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      
        <category term="energy" />
      
        <category term="electric" />
      
        <category term="cars" />
      
        <category term="world" />
      
        <category term="EV" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">In an earlier post, we learnt something that we do not see everyday, even if we work in a coal mine, as the variety of energy and the consumption end points blind us from looking at the full picture. Today, we will look at some trends that we see all around us, all the time - Electric vehicles (EVs). For most of us, an electric car immediately reminds us of Tesla - the innovative American automobile manufacturer that is to become the world’s most valuable automobile company very soon. Tesla is also the company that created an electric car revolution. Tesla’s success, in many ways, drove other automakers to accelerate their offering of all-electric products. We saw that the transition was not overnight. Many built hybrid vehicles (HEV), range-extended electric vehicles, plug-in hybrid vehicles (PHEV), before building all electric, or battery electric vehicles (BEV). However, if one is to guess which country on the planet has the most number of electric cars it would most likely be the US or EU, because of Tesla and the likes of VW or BMW (both of which make electric cars). Let’s see how the actual answer unfolds. IEA’s global outlook and data show some impressive numbers. To quote from their report, Only about 17 000 electric cars were on the world’s roads in 2010. By 2019, that number had swelled to 7.2 million, 47% of which were in The People’s Republic of China. Further, despite purchase subsidies for electric cars were cut in many geographies (like tax credits in the US) and the resulting drop in electric car sales, the total number electric vehicles in China, EU and the US are still very impressive - 2.58 million BEVs in China compared to 0.88 million BEVs in the US and 0.97 million BEVs in the EU. One would start thinking what other industries are getting transformed along with the transformation of automotive industry. The implications of this transformation are huge touching several industries from service industry, retail and insurance. The analysis of the transformation itself would give fascninating insights. That would be the topic of a future post.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Covid vs Coal →</title>
      
      <link href="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/06/01/covid-vs-coal/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Covid vs Coal" />
      <published>2020-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://dotkay.github.io/2020/06/01/covid-vs-coal</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/06/01/covid-vs-coal/">&lt;p&gt;I was listening to an interesting news program on renewable energy recently that made claims and projections about the current state and future of energy - primarily about renewable energy overtaking coal as the major source of energy. As a result of Covid, demand for electricity has fallen and as coal has become more and more expensive than renewable counterparts, coal based electricity is facing an uphill battle. Will coal survive the covid crisis, in developed countries, is yet to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This prompted me to dig further into the data on energy production and consumption in the US. I was indeed surprised to see that coal based energy production is in fact decreasing in the US, and is decreasing drastically. I was surpised by two factors. First, I thought only under-developed or developing countries were the places where coal based energy was a major source, primarily due to the lack of infrastructure (like efficient transmission grids) and the cost of renewable energy (solar panels, wind turbines, etc.). Second, nuclear power production has flattened out somewhere in the last decade, and is now overtaken by renewable energy. With several nuclear power plants built over the decades, some of them dangerously &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nbcnews.com/id/42103936/ns/world_news-asia_pacific/t/what-are-odds-us-nuke-plants-ranked-quake-risk/&quot;&gt;close to fault lines&lt;/a&gt;, I was expecting more energy to be generated by nuclear plants. It turned out that was not the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the data, coal production is indeed decreasing and at such a rate that it is almost close to what it was in the 1950s. While renewable energy is all set to overtake coal based energy and experts predict 2020 to be the year for this to happen. In fact, renewable energy production has already overtaken nuclear energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/energy/coal_vs_renewable.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Coal vs Renewable Energy&quot; class=&quot;img=responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the above is certainly positive news, there are several other fossil fuels (natural gas, crude oil, etc.) just like there are several renewable energy sources (hydroelectric,  solar, wind, etc.). Looking at more details at the different sources of fossil fuels, although coal production has reduced, total fossil fuel production is still way more than renewable energy production as the following chart shows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/energy/fossil_vs_renewable.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Fossil Fuels vs Renewable Energy&quot; class=&quot;img=responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for more insights into energy production and consumption in residential and transportation sectors.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      
        <category term="energy" />
      
        <category term="coal" />
      
        <category term="renewable energy" />
      
        <category term="US" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">I was listening to an interesting news program on renewable energy recently that made claims and projections about the current state and future of energy - primarily about renewable energy overtaking coal as the major source of energy. As a result of Covid, demand for electricity has fallen and as coal has become more and more expensive than renewable counterparts, coal based electricity is facing an uphill battle. Will coal survive the covid crisis, in developed countries, is yet to be seen. This prompted me to dig further into the data on energy production and consumption in the US. I was indeed surprised to see that coal based energy production is in fact decreasing in the US, and is decreasing drastically. I was surpised by two factors. First, I thought only under-developed or developing countries were the places where coal based energy was a major source, primarily due to the lack of infrastructure (like efficient transmission grids) and the cost of renewable energy (solar panels, wind turbines, etc.). Second, nuclear power production has flattened out somewhere in the last decade, and is now overtaken by renewable energy. With several nuclear power plants built over the decades, some of them dangerously close to fault lines, I was expecting more energy to be generated by nuclear plants. It turned out that was not the case. Looking at the data, coal production is indeed decreasing and at such a rate that it is almost close to what it was in the 1950s. While renewable energy is all set to overtake coal based energy and experts predict 2020 to be the year for this to happen. In fact, renewable energy production has already overtaken nuclear energy. While the above is certainly positive news, there are several other fossil fuels (natural gas, crude oil, etc.) just like there are several renewable energy sources (hydroelectric, solar, wind, etc.). Looking at more details at the different sources of fossil fuels, although coal production has reduced, total fossil fuel production is still way more than renewable energy production as the following chart shows. Stay tuned for more insights into energy production and consumption in residential and transportation sectors.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Online Education - ‘Right’ing the Privilege →</title>
      
      <link href="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/05/25/online-education-part-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Online Education - 'Right'ing the Privilege" />
      <published>2020-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://dotkay.github.io/2020/05/25/online-education-part-1</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/05/25/online-education-part-1/">&lt;p&gt;As we have been watching over the years, quality education no longer requires us to move to a different city to attend a quality university. It is available right on our smart device. With several universities around the world having some set of courses that are offered online and with the growth of several companies like Udacity, Coursera, Udemy and the like offering MOOCs (Massive Open Online Courses) the scale of reach for quality education is also much bigger - after all no university classroom is equipped to handle a million students simultaneously. So it is fair to say that anyone anywhere can get access to quality education right at their fingertips. Or is it? Are we missing something else?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The COVID pandemic has exposed the inqualities, not only in employment but also in access to quality education. With several schools shut, the only options several schools have is to deliver their courses online. While many schools themselves are not well equipped to deliver education as a digital service, many more students and their households do not have the means to provide them with the necessary infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study, McKinsey &amp;amp; Co. compared 6th grade performance under different scenarios - returning to classrooms in 2020, early 2021 and mid 2021 and the results are shocking. The report also computes the average months of learning lost, due to low-quality remote learning, to be about 7-11 months even if schools open in early 2021 for in person learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dotkay/tmp/main/misc/mckinsey_6th_grade_school.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report also says that this can have a drastic impact on the future of students and thereby the GDP of the country, due to many students dropping out of school due to their inability to access education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dotkay/tmp/main/misc/mckinsey_gdp_loss_due_to_school.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And these results might just be the tip of the iceberg. Even if the government is able to subsidise infrastructure needs for online education over the next several months, that alone is not going to solve the problem. The dynamics of online education, especially for younger children, have many challenges:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is a certain energy that is brought about by many teachers in the physical classroom, that motivates students to listen and learn. This is difficult for many teachers to replicate online.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Just as not every YouTube video is interesting not every subject is going to be equally interesting when listened to online.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attention span of students away from a regular, formal school environment is going to be different (lower) and this would reduce the learning experience as well as the knowledge gained.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many schools and teachers may not be proficient or may not have the workforce to deal with the many system administration issues that need to be tackled in real-time for delivering classes online.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accessing such online education also requires relatively stable devices - even if chromebooks are relatively cheaper, many households - especially in the developing world where tablets and chromebooks are still a discretionary expense.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many parts of the developing world also do not have the necessary internet infrastructure to handle streaming videos at a large scale. Note that the number of students in a class in the developing world is also large.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moving from blackboard teaching to digital content creation takes time and it is not always easy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some topics, like biology or chemistry labs, just cannot happen through remote learning.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Students with learning disabilities would need the teacher in person in order to be able to learn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given these various challenges and the data and projections provided in McKinsey &amp;amp; Co.’s report, it is fair to say that (online) education is still a privilege and not a right. What possible solutions could local governments, corporations and teachers come up with?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Governments&lt;/strong&gt; could fast track the implementation of broadband networks, possibly by subsidising companies to do so in case the government is not able to do it themselves. Many other services, besides education, rely on efficient internet infrastructure and in the years to come, the number of services dependent on such infrastructure is only going to increase. They could also provide low income households with computing devices so that they can access education when delivered digitally. This reminds me of the days when state governments in India provided bicycles to students in government schools so that they can commute and access education provided in far away schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Corporations&lt;/strong&gt; could make devices exclusively for school students. These need to be rugged, inexpensive and with a long battery life. In order for this to be feasible as a business, corporations could:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make the devices modular so that one could collect back damaged or older devices, recycle the parts into refurbished devices.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sacrifice non-essential elements that add up to the price (like different sets of fancy ports, etc.) for longer battery life and higher quality.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Partner with school districts to loan such devices which could be collected back periodically for refurbishing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collaborate on creating uniform content creation tools that would enable the teachers to create interesting content faster.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Help teachers create engaging content from their knowledge of YouTube or Coursera views and feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teachers&lt;/strong&gt; could learn to create engaging digital content - stories, animations and charts that would capture the interests of students, increasing their attention span even when in an environment different from regular classrooms. Teachers could:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collaborate and share content so that they can spend more time focussing on students’ development and learning than creating content.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collaborate and share best practices so that new teachers or even volunteers can get better at keeping the students engaged and teach.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a big role parents play in such situations, along with teachers. These are extraordinary times - while technologies like Zoom and Cloud computing allow many of us to work remotely, education is one domain where despite technological advancements several challenges remain to be solved.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      
        <category term="online" />
      
        <category term="education" />
      
        <category term="inequality" />
      
        <category term="MOOC" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">As we have been watching over the years, quality education no longer requires us to move to a different city to attend a quality university. It is available right on our smart device. With several universities around the world having some set of courses that are offered online and with the growth of several companies like Udacity, Coursera, Udemy and the like offering MOOCs (Massive Open Online Courses) the scale of reach for quality education is also much bigger - after all no university classroom is equipped to handle a million students simultaneously. So it is fair to say that anyone anywhere can get access to quality education right at their fingertips. Or is it? Are we missing something else? The COVID pandemic has exposed the inqualities, not only in employment but also in access to quality education. With several schools shut, the only options several schools have is to deliver their courses online. While many schools themselves are not well equipped to deliver education as a digital service, many more students and their households do not have the means to provide them with the necessary infrastructure. In a study, McKinsey &amp;amp; Co. compared 6th grade performance under different scenarios - returning to classrooms in 2020, early 2021 and mid 2021 and the results are shocking. The report also computes the average months of learning lost, due to low-quality remote learning, to be about 7-11 months even if schools open in early 2021 for in person learning. The report also says that this can have a drastic impact on the future of students and thereby the GDP of the country, due to many students dropping out of school due to their inability to access education. And these results might just be the tip of the iceberg. Even if the government is able to subsidise infrastructure needs for online education over the next several months, that alone is not going to solve the problem. The dynamics of online education, especially for younger children, have many challenges: There is a certain energy that is brought about by many teachers in the physical classroom, that motivates students to listen and learn. This is difficult for many teachers to replicate online. Just as not every YouTube video is interesting not every subject is going to be equally interesting when listened to online. Attention span of students away from a regular, formal school environment is going to be different (lower) and this would reduce the learning experience as well as the knowledge gained. Many schools and teachers may not be proficient or may not have the workforce to deal with the many system administration issues that need to be tackled in real-time for delivering classes online. Accessing such online education also requires relatively stable devices - even if chromebooks are relatively cheaper, many households - especially in the developing world where tablets and chromebooks are still a discretionary expense. Many parts of the developing world also do not have the necessary internet infrastructure to handle streaming videos at a large scale. Note that the number of students in a class in the developing world is also large. Moving from blackboard teaching to digital content creation takes time and it is not always easy. Some topics, like biology or chemistry labs, just cannot happen through remote learning. Students with learning disabilities would need the teacher in person in order to be able to learn Given these various challenges and the data and projections provided in McKinsey &amp;amp; Co.’s report, it is fair to say that (online) education is still a privilege and not a right. What possible solutions could local governments, corporations and teachers come up with? Governments could fast track the implementation of broadband networks, possibly by subsidising companies to do so in case the government is not able to do it themselves. Many other services, besides education, rely on efficient internet infrastructure and in the years to come, the number of services dependent on such infrastructure is only going to increase. They could also provide low income households with computing devices so that they can access education when delivered digitally. This reminds me of the days when state governments in India provided bicycles to students in government schools so that they can commute and access education provided in far away schools. Corporations could make devices exclusively for school students. These need to be rugged, inexpensive and with a long battery life. In order for this to be feasible as a business, corporations could: Make the devices modular so that one could collect back damaged or older devices, recycle the parts into refurbished devices. Sacrifice non-essential elements that add up to the price (like different sets of fancy ports, etc.) for longer battery life and higher quality. Partner with school districts to loan such devices which could be collected back periodically for refurbishing. Collaborate on creating uniform content creation tools that would enable the teachers to create interesting content faster. Help teachers create engaging content from their knowledge of YouTube or Coursera views and feedback. Teachers could learn to create engaging digital content - stories, animations and charts that would capture the interests of students, increasing their attention span even when in an environment different from regular classrooms. Teachers could: Collaborate and share content so that they can spend more time focussing on students’ development and learning than creating content. Collaborate and share best practices so that new teachers or even volunteers can get better at keeping the students engaged and teach. There is also a big role parents play in such situations, along with teachers. These are extraordinary times - while technologies like Zoom and Cloud computing allow many of us to work remotely, education is one domain where despite technological advancements several challenges remain to be solved.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Streaming vs Cinemas in a post COVID world →</title>
      
      <link href="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/05/05/streaming-vs-cinema-post-covid/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Streaming vs Cinemas in a post COVID world" />
      <published>2020-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://dotkay.github.io/2020/05/05/streaming-vs-cinema-post-covid</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/05/05/streaming-vs-cinema-post-covid/">&lt;p&gt;Watching a movie with stunning visual special effects, sound effects is best done in cinema halls. The screens are wide, the hall geometry and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theaterseatstore.com/blog/movie-sound-systems&quot;&gt;sound technologies&lt;/a&gt; like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Surround_sound&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;surrond sound&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; add to the experience. It is no surprise that movies like Jurrasic Park, Inception, Avengers, etc. are best watched on large screen, in cinemas. It is not just the story, it is the movie experience, besides the social aspect of being outside and the lights going down. US box office revenues were 11.32 billion USD in 2019 and 11.89 billion USD in 2018 (all time best).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lately, streaming has become very popular. It gives the convenience of watching the movie as and when one wanted, without having to drive to a cinema and at much lower price. A family of four can watch several movies in their living room for a monthly service fee of about $15, while a movie ticket would cost each of the family members as much. Added to this would be popcorn and soda. Netflix and lately almost every major studio is into streaming. Traditionally, movies were run in cinemas for about 90 days before getting released in digital format. But that 90 day “windowing” is coming under a lot of pressure with many streaming services deciding to release the movies right away in digital format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we have two interesting and opposing forces - cinema halls and streaming services. One provides the best experience while the other provides convenience and affordability. And then came the COVID pandemic. With cinema halls being the sort of place that by design invited a large gathering in an enclosed room, it provided the perfect recipe for a pandemic spread. Cinema halls are closed and people are stuck at home having not much of an entertainment - a perfect recipe for streaming services to be at their best to relieve those sheltering in place of their boredom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As if the scenario is not interesting enough, it was rumored that a popular movie streaming service - Amazon Prime Video made a bid for a popular cinema chain AMC. Although nothing of this is confirmed, the very thought process in analyzing this is interesting. What would be Amazon’s interest in AMC?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amazon has a sizeable number of prime customers who get free shipping on goods and some deals on Whole Foods stores. Would Amazon give them monthly passes or subsidized tickets to watch movies in AMC?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amazon Studios makes originals. Would those originals first be released in AMC and later streamed on Amazon Prime?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Would Amazon reserve AMC for the first few weeks, for movies with stellar visual and sound effects?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Would Amazon split the Studio products into TV shows like soaps for Amazon Prime and movies for AMC?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Would AMC become a Hollywood talent scouting arm for Amazon?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all these, how would the pricing work? Amazon is known for maximizing efficiency and getting the best price for the end customer. Would it be able to replicate it in box office movies? If so, how? It is an interesting aspect waiting to be seen, if the rumours are true and if the deal goes through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Till then, relax on your couch and stream your favorite shows.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      
        <category term="streaming" />
      
        <category term="cinema" />
      
        <category term="box office" />
      
        <category term="Netflix" />
      
        <category term="Amazon" />
      
        <category term="AMC" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">Watching a movie with stunning visual special effects, sound effects is best done in cinema halls. The screens are wide, the hall geometry and sound technologies like surrond sound add to the experience. It is no surprise that movies like Jurrasic Park, Inception, Avengers, etc. are best watched on large screen, in cinemas. It is not just the story, it is the movie experience, besides the social aspect of being outside and the lights going down. US box office revenues were 11.32 billion USD in 2019 and 11.89 billion USD in 2018 (all time best). Lately, streaming has become very popular. It gives the convenience of watching the movie as and when one wanted, without having to drive to a cinema and at much lower price. A family of four can watch several movies in their living room for a monthly service fee of about $15, while a movie ticket would cost each of the family members as much. Added to this would be popcorn and soda. Netflix and lately almost every major studio is into streaming. Traditionally, movies were run in cinemas for about 90 days before getting released in digital format. But that 90 day “windowing” is coming under a lot of pressure with many streaming services deciding to release the movies right away in digital format. So, we have two interesting and opposing forces - cinema halls and streaming services. One provides the best experience while the other provides convenience and affordability. And then came the COVID pandemic. With cinema halls being the sort of place that by design invited a large gathering in an enclosed room, it provided the perfect recipe for a pandemic spread. Cinema halls are closed and people are stuck at home having not much of an entertainment - a perfect recipe for streaming services to be at their best to relieve those sheltering in place of their boredom. As if the scenario is not interesting enough, it was rumored that a popular movie streaming service - Amazon Prime Video made a bid for a popular cinema chain AMC. Although nothing of this is confirmed, the very thought process in analyzing this is interesting. What would be Amazon’s interest in AMC? Amazon has a sizeable number of prime customers who get free shipping on goods and some deals on Whole Foods stores. Would Amazon give them monthly passes or subsidized tickets to watch movies in AMC? Amazon Studios makes originals. Would those originals first be released in AMC and later streamed on Amazon Prime? Would Amazon reserve AMC for the first few weeks, for movies with stellar visual and sound effects? Would Amazon split the Studio products into TV shows like soaps for Amazon Prime and movies for AMC? Would AMC become a Hollywood talent scouting arm for Amazon? In all these, how would the pricing work? Amazon is known for maximizing efficiency and getting the best price for the end customer. Would it be able to replicate it in box office movies? If so, how? It is an interesting aspect waiting to be seen, if the rumours are true and if the deal goes through. Till then, relax on your couch and stream your favorite shows.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Efficiency vs Flexibility →</title>
      
      <link href="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/04/01/efficiency-vs-flexibility/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Efficiency vs Flexibility" />
      <published>2020-04-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://dotkay.github.io/2020/04/01/efficiency-vs-flexibility</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/04/01/efficiency-vs-flexibility/">&lt;p&gt;Despite the date of posting, this post isn’t a joke and is meant to provoke some thoughts on efficiency and flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of COVID-19 pandemic we saw the mad rush for toilet papers and other essentials that were getting swept off super-market shelves. Not just toilet papers, even face-masks and ventilators were in short supply at a time when they were most needed. Many consumer and semiconductor companies lowered their guidance due to disruptions in their supply chain. How did we get into a situation where so many industries - from toilet papers to iPhones were getting affected?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world over the many years got more globalized. American or Canadian products were not made in the US or Canada. They were made in places where it was cheaper and faster to make. Even &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/360e2524-d71a-11e8-a854-33d6f82e62f8&quot;&gt;trash is sent to other countries&lt;/a&gt; in order to be recycled in a cost-effective manner. In short, global supply chain over the years shaped its goal into one that is more cost efficient rather than being flexible. This is not the first time companies are facing shocks. Not long ago, floods in Japan resulted in supply chain issues for automotive companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this design for efficiency a problem? It definitely looks like, given what many countries went through as the COVID-19 pandemic stuck. Many companies were not able to reliably source their material and keep their assembly lines busy, as they were over-invested in the most (cost) efficient supply chains like in China. If instead the supply chains were designed for flexibility, the average marginal cost of a product “might be” (and just might be) a little higher but geography specific events would not throw the entire system out of gear. There is an emphasis on the uncertainity of the cost implications as it is not entirely clear at this point. For example, one could argue that, if the semiconductor industry had sourced from several geographies like China, India, Africa, South America, etc., it is very likely that the infrastructure for sustaining such supply chains would have developed in many such countries creating a healthy competition, thereby reducing the cost. And this applies to several industries, not just semiconductors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have the corporates learnt a lesson now?. There was a similar talk after supply chain disruptions in Japan, but nothing materialized in the long run. Would this time be different? One has to wait and watch.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      
        <category term="efficiency" />
      
        <category term="flexibility" />
      
        <category term="globalization" />
      
        <category term="supply chain" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">Despite the date of posting, this post isn’t a joke and is meant to provoke some thoughts on efficiency and flexibility. As a result of COVID-19 pandemic we saw the mad rush for toilet papers and other essentials that were getting swept off super-market shelves. Not just toilet papers, even face-masks and ventilators were in short supply at a time when they were most needed. Many consumer and semiconductor companies lowered their guidance due to disruptions in their supply chain. How did we get into a situation where so many industries - from toilet papers to iPhones were getting affected? The world over the many years got more globalized. American or Canadian products were not made in the US or Canada. They were made in places where it was cheaper and faster to make. Even trash is sent to other countries in order to be recycled in a cost-effective manner. In short, global supply chain over the years shaped its goal into one that is more cost efficient rather than being flexible. This is not the first time companies are facing shocks. Not long ago, floods in Japan resulted in supply chain issues for automotive companies. Is this design for efficiency a problem? It definitely looks like, given what many countries went through as the COVID-19 pandemic stuck. Many companies were not able to reliably source their material and keep their assembly lines busy, as they were over-invested in the most (cost) efficient supply chains like in China. If instead the supply chains were designed for flexibility, the average marginal cost of a product “might be” (and just might be) a little higher but geography specific events would not throw the entire system out of gear. There is an emphasis on the uncertainity of the cost implications as it is not entirely clear at this point. For example, one could argue that, if the semiconductor industry had sourced from several geographies like China, India, Africa, South America, etc., it is very likely that the infrastructure for sustaining such supply chains would have developed in many such countries creating a healthy competition, thereby reducing the cost. And this applies to several industries, not just semiconductors. Have the corporates learnt a lesson now?. There was a similar talk after supply chain disruptions in Japan, but nothing materialized in the long run. Would this time be different? One has to wait and watch.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Market Returns and Regression Betas →</title>
      
      <link href="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/03/15/market-returns-and-regression-betas/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Market Returns and Regression Betas" />
      <published>2020-03-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://dotkay.github.io/2020/03/15/market-returns-and-regression-betas</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/03/15/market-returns-and-regression-betas/">&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://dotkay.github.io/2020/03/01/market-returns-and-stocks&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; we saw how volatile a stock is, compared to a broader market performance, by plotting the percentage change in weekly returns of the stock prices. We were able to visually see that a certain stock was moving much more vigorously than the market (S&amp;amp;P 500 in that case).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I want to see how to find and measure the movement of a particular stock with respect to the market. Is there a standardized measure? Suppose an investor who holds multiple assets wants to measure how much risk &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; particular asset adds to his portfolio, is there a way he can quantify the risk?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Statistically, &lt;em&gt;covariance&lt;/em&gt; of an asset measures how much the asset moves compared to market movements&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Beta&lt;/em&gt; is a standardized measure of this covariance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;        covariance of asset with market 
Beta =  ---------------------------------
            variance of the market
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we have market returns data that we used in our previous plot, we can run a regression on this data and try to fit a straight line to the data points in our dataset. The slope of the regression is the &lt;em&gt;Beta&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;R_asset = alpha + beta * R_market
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statsmodels.org&quot;&gt;statsmodels&lt;/a&gt; library to compute a linear regression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;statsmodels.api&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sm&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sp500_returns&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;nvda_returns&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;add_constant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;nvda_reg&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;OLS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;endog&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;exog&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;nvda_reg_model&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;nvda_reg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;nvda_reg_model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;summary&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;())&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;                            OLS Regression Results                            
==============================================================================
Dep. Variable:              Adj Close   R-squared:                       0.265
Model:                            OLS   Adj. R-squared:                  0.262
Method:                 Least Squares   F-statistic:                     93.11
                                        Prob (F-statistic):           5.21e-19
                                        Log-Likelihood:                 414.26
No. Observations:                 260   AIC:                            -824.5
Df Residuals:                     258   BIC:                            -817.4
Df Model:                           1                                         
Covariance Type:            nonrobust                                         
==============================================================================
                 coef    std err          t      P&amp;gt;|t|      [0.025      0.975]
------------------------------------------------------------------------------
const          0.0080      0.003      2.598      0.010       0.002       0.014
Adj Close      1.7961      0.186      9.649      0.000       1.430       2.163
==============================================================================
Omnibus:                       73.992   Durbin-Watson:                   2.085
Prob(Omnibus):                  0.000   Jarque-Bera (JB):              639.151
Skew:                           0.846   Prob(JB):                    1.62e-139
Kurtosis:                      10.492   Cond. No.                         60.8
==============================================================================

Notes:
[1] Standard Errors assume that the covariance matrix of the errors is correctly specified.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we used (percentage change in ) &lt;em&gt;adjusted closing prices&lt;/em&gt; in our returns (with the column name ‘Adj Close’ in our dataframe), we see that the &lt;em&gt;beta&lt;/em&gt; of NVIDIA stock during the period of the regression (2015-2019) is &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1.79&lt;/code&gt;. We also see the R-squared value of our regression which turns out to be 0.265 and this indicates that 26.5% of the risk can be attributed to the market risk while the remaining &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;73.5%&lt;/code&gt; of the risk is firm specific. We also see the P value of our regression and a bunch of other details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can also plot our regression:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;jointplot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sp500_returns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;nvda_returns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
                 &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;kind&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;reg&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fit_reg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
                 &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;height&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
                 &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;marginal_kws&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;dict&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bins&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dotkay/fin_data_analysis/main/beta.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are an investor and you are given a choice between two stocks having the same beta but very different R-squared - which one would you choose and why?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      
        <category term="S&amp;P 500" />
      
        <category term="market returns" />
      
        <category term="regression" />
      
        <category term="beta" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">In a previous post we saw how volatile a stock is, compared to a broader market performance, by plotting the percentage change in weekly returns of the stock prices. We were able to visually see that a certain stock was moving much more vigorously than the market (S&amp;amp;P 500 in that case). In this post, I want to see how to find and measure the movement of a particular stock with respect to the market. Is there a standardized measure? Suppose an investor who holds multiple assets wants to measure how much risk a particular asset adds to his portfolio, is there a way he can quantify the risk? Statistically, covariance of an asset measures how much the asset moves compared to market movements Beta is a standardized measure of this covariance. covariance of asset with market Beta = --------------------------------- variance of the market Since we have market returns data that we used in our previous plot, we can run a regression on this data and try to fit a straight line to the data points in our dataset. The slope of the regression is the Beta. R_asset = alpha + beta * R_market Let us use the statsmodels library to compute a linear regression. import statsmodels.api as sm ... x = sp500_returns y = nvda_returns x = sm.add_constant(x) nvda_reg = sm.OLS(endog=y, exog=x) nvda_reg_model = nvda_reg.fit() print(nvda_reg_model.summary()) OLS Regression Results ============================================================================== Dep. Variable: Adj Close R-squared: 0.265 Model: OLS Adj. R-squared: 0.262 Method: Least Squares F-statistic: 93.11 Prob (F-statistic): 5.21e-19 Log-Likelihood: 414.26 No. Observations: 260 AIC: -824.5 Df Residuals: 258 BIC: -817.4 Df Model: 1 Covariance Type: nonrobust ============================================================================== coef std err t P&amp;gt;|t| [0.025 0.975] ------------------------------------------------------------------------------ const 0.0080 0.003 2.598 0.010 0.002 0.014 Adj Close 1.7961 0.186 9.649 0.000 1.430 2.163 ============================================================================== Omnibus: 73.992 Durbin-Watson: 2.085 Prob(Omnibus): 0.000 Jarque-Bera (JB): 639.151 Skew: 0.846 Prob(JB): 1.62e-139 Kurtosis: 10.492 Cond. No. 60.8 ============================================================================== Notes: [1] Standard Errors assume that the covariance matrix of the errors is correctly specified. Since we used (percentage change in ) adjusted closing prices in our returns (with the column name ‘Adj Close’ in our dataframe), we see that the beta of NVIDIA stock during the period of the regression (2015-2019) is 1.79. We also see the R-squared value of our regression which turns out to be 0.265 and this indicates that 26.5% of the risk can be attributed to the market risk while the remaining 73.5% of the risk is firm specific. We also see the P value of our regression and a bunch of other details. We can also plot our regression: p = sns.jointplot(x = sp500_returns, y = nvda_returns, kind = &quot;reg&quot;, fit_reg=True, height = 20, marginal_kws = dict(bins=100)) ... If you are an investor and you are given a choice between two stocks having the same beta but very different R-squared - which one would you choose and why?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Market Returns and Stock Prices →</title>
      
      <link href="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/03/01/market-returns-and-stocks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Market Returns and Stock Prices" />
      <published>2020-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://dotkay.github.io/2020/03/01/market-returns-and-stocks</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/03/01/market-returns-and-stocks/">&lt;p&gt;I recently started learning about stock prices, market returns and how risk is measured. I am still in the process of learning about it and I hope to add more to my knowledge in the following months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many stock indices to look for how the general market is performing. More often, we hear about DOW index (DJIA - Dow Jones Industrial Average) down or NASDAQ up and so on. But NASDAQ is a technology firm heavy listing - i.e. the movement of the NASDAQ index would indicate the movement of technology sector to a large extent. While DJIA is a more general mix of stocks, it is price weighted and so companies with a higher stock price or extreme price movements would influence the movement more. Another common index is the S&amp;amp;P 500 (Standard and Poor’s 500) Index. S&amp;amp;P 500 is weighted by market value of the companies rather than the stock prices. So, a 5% movement of a $200 stock would affect the index the same way as a 5% movement of a $100 stock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us see how the weekly percentage change in returns of one of the stocks (NVDA) compares to the percentage returns of the S&amp;amp;P 500 returns (usually referred to as &lt;em&gt;market returns&lt;/em&gt;), over a period of about five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sp500_returns&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sp500_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Adj Close'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pct_change&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;nvda_returns&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;nvda_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Adj Close'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pct_change&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sp500_returns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;label&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'S&amp;amp;P 500'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;nvda_returns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;label&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'NVDA'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dotkay/fin_data_analysis/main/nvda_vs_sp500.PNG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above plot shows you how much NVDA (NVIDIA stock prices) fluctuate more than the general market (S&amp;amp;P 500 price index). If the stock is too volatile, it might be because of some risk associated with that stock, some portion of which can be explained by market movements and some portion specific to the company’s internal risk. &lt;em&gt;Beta&lt;/em&gt; is typically used as a measure of risk, which we will compute in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      
        <category term="S&amp;P 500" />
      
        <category term="DJIA" />
      
        <category term="stock market" />
      
        <category term="returns" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">I recently started learning about stock prices, market returns and how risk is measured. I am still in the process of learning about it and I hope to add more to my knowledge in the following months. There are many stock indices to look for how the general market is performing. More often, we hear about DOW index (DJIA - Dow Jones Industrial Average) down or NASDAQ up and so on. But NASDAQ is a technology firm heavy listing - i.e. the movement of the NASDAQ index would indicate the movement of technology sector to a large extent. While DJIA is a more general mix of stocks, it is price weighted and so companies with a higher stock price or extreme price movements would influence the movement more. Another common index is the S&amp;amp;P 500 (Standard and Poor’s 500) Index. S&amp;amp;P 500 is weighted by market value of the companies rather than the stock prices. So, a 5% movement of a $200 stock would affect the index the same way as a 5% movement of a $100 stock. Let us see how the weekly percentage change in returns of one of the stocks (NVDA) compares to the percentage returns of the S&amp;amp;P 500 returns (usually referred to as market returns), over a period of about five years. ... sp500_returns = sp500_df['Adj Close'].pct_change()[1:] nvda_returns = nvda_df['Adj Close'].pct_change()[1:] ... ... sp500_returns.plot(label='S&amp;amp;P 500') nvda_returns.plot(label='NVDA') The above plot shows you how much NVDA (NVIDIA stock prices) fluctuate more than the general market (S&amp;amp;P 500 price index). If the stock is too volatile, it might be because of some risk associated with that stock, some portion of which can be explained by market movements and some portion specific to the company’s internal risk. Beta is typically used as a measure of risk, which we will compute in a future post.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">The Evolution of Search Advertising →</title>
      
      <link href="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/02/28/evolution-of-search-advertising/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Evolution of Search Advertising" />
      <published>2020-02-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://dotkay.github.io/2020/02/28/evolution-of-search-advertising</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/02/28/evolution-of-search-advertising/">&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://dotkay.github.io/2020/02/01/evolution-of-search&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, we saw how internet search evolved from being a generic search application to specialized ones. We also saw how there are also apps that provided bundled search experience but by being a gateway (or gatekeeper) to several specialized search services. With search advertising being one of the most lucrative business to be in, there are large implications from the experience, relevance and the quality of the search results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dotkay/tmp/main/misc/search_advertising.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The search experience and relevance of search results depends on what one is searching for and what extras go with the main search. Searching for a baseball game in a stadium has more likelihood with pizzas or dining places (to grab a bite on your way to the stadium or dine on way back home), while searching for a baseball game on TV goes well with doordash like home delivery or inviting friends over (via a social app). The geographical aspirations and interests that depend on age also matter a lot. Youngsters are more likely to search for fast-food while the elderly might search for baking needs and recipes. Youngsters might search for camping and youth hostels while others would want to visit museums and other historical sites while staying in hotels closer to the city. Youngsters might search for escape rooms while the elderly might look for concerts and plays. Of course, it is not as black and white as described and it is always a large spectrum of interests, age, location and cultural preferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bundled and unbundled search has huge implications on the search advertising. Instead of advertising in one available avenue (a generic search engine), there are specific applications where one could do targeted advertising. I am very likely to search for a restaurant on Yelp, a movie rating on IMDB, books on Amazon, taxi service on Uber, take-away food on Doordash, etc. What this means is that some of the advertising dollars move away from Google to the specialized search apps. Further the data acquired by these specialized search apps may remain separate making them serve more relevant results and improve search experience. That is one of the reasons one searches for restaurant ratings in Yelp and a doormat’s rating on Amazon. While this might make us assume specialized apps might be the only way to go, all-in-one search apps like WeChat (MiniProgram) act as a gatekeeper to many of the services - in many cases the services can be accessed only through WeChat. This might allow such an app to aggregate user preferences from the different services, profile the interests and allow for cross-selling or upselling dynamic advertisements. Such an aggregation of data from the different services (from within an app) also allows to curate advertisements that would target the specific user’s interests. If he has consistently bought pizza take-out every Friday evening, Uber app could advertise pizza take-away stores on the user’s ride back home on Friday evening, and probably suggest some highly rated movies to watch along with eating his pizza. In the absence of such a nexus between the services, there could be other ways of stitching together the different pieces of information (like payment apps, GPS and mapping data, communication apps, etc.) to build a user profile. News feeds further complicate the search, by being more dynamic and real-time and sensitive to user preferences and interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the discussion of privacy. How does one use the data in such a way that any individual information is not let out, without affecting the quality of the search results. Lately, privacy is a huge concern among technology companies and has hence renewed interest in the topic. Technologies for ensuring privacy without compromising search quality would be a topic of a future post.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      
        <category term="search" />
      
        <category term="internet" />
      
        <category term="advertising" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">In a previous post, we saw how internet search evolved from being a generic search application to specialized ones. We also saw how there are also apps that provided bundled search experience but by being a gateway (or gatekeeper) to several specialized search services. With search advertising being one of the most lucrative business to be in, there are large implications from the experience, relevance and the quality of the search results. The search experience and relevance of search results depends on what one is searching for and what extras go with the main search. Searching for a baseball game in a stadium has more likelihood with pizzas or dining places (to grab a bite on your way to the stadium or dine on way back home), while searching for a baseball game on TV goes well with doordash like home delivery or inviting friends over (via a social app). The geographical aspirations and interests that depend on age also matter a lot. Youngsters are more likely to search for fast-food while the elderly might search for baking needs and recipes. Youngsters might search for camping and youth hostels while others would want to visit museums and other historical sites while staying in hotels closer to the city. Youngsters might search for escape rooms while the elderly might look for concerts and plays. Of course, it is not as black and white as described and it is always a large spectrum of interests, age, location and cultural preferences. Bundled and unbundled search has huge implications on the search advertising. Instead of advertising in one available avenue (a generic search engine), there are specific applications where one could do targeted advertising. I am very likely to search for a restaurant on Yelp, a movie rating on IMDB, books on Amazon, taxi service on Uber, take-away food on Doordash, etc. What this means is that some of the advertising dollars move away from Google to the specialized search apps. Further the data acquired by these specialized search apps may remain separate making them serve more relevant results and improve search experience. That is one of the reasons one searches for restaurant ratings in Yelp and a doormat’s rating on Amazon. While this might make us assume specialized apps might be the only way to go, all-in-one search apps like WeChat (MiniProgram) act as a gatekeeper to many of the services - in many cases the services can be accessed only through WeChat. This might allow such an app to aggregate user preferences from the different services, profile the interests and allow for cross-selling or upselling dynamic advertisements. Such an aggregation of data from the different services (from within an app) also allows to curate advertisements that would target the specific user’s interests. If he has consistently bought pizza take-out every Friday evening, Uber app could advertise pizza take-away stores on the user’s ride back home on Friday evening, and probably suggest some highly rated movies to watch along with eating his pizza. In the absence of such a nexus between the services, there could be other ways of stitching together the different pieces of information (like payment apps, GPS and mapping data, communication apps, etc.) to build a user profile. News feeds further complicate the search, by being more dynamic and real-time and sensitive to user preferences and interests. This brings us to the discussion of privacy. How does one use the data in such a way that any individual information is not let out, without affecting the quality of the search results. Lately, privacy is a huge concern among technology companies and has hence renewed interest in the topic. Technologies for ensuring privacy without compromising search quality would be a topic of a future post.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">The Evolution of Internet Search →</title>
      
      <link href="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/02/01/evolution-of-search/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Evolution of Internet Search" />
      <published>2020-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://dotkay.github.io/2020/02/01/evolution-of-search</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://dotkay.github.io/2020/02/01/evolution-of-search/">&lt;p&gt;Over the last couple of decades, internet search has evolved a lot. This evolution has several facets - on one hand technology changes like Web 2.0, semantic web, richer media, etc., and on the other hand going from generic to specific - or unbundling and bundling of search.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early days of search engines, one would search every generic thing on the search engine application. If we want to see if there are good Pizzerias near our hotel during a trip to Paris, we would look for pizzerias in Paris and whichever fancy restaurant had made an effort to create a website (a static one) might show up. As technologies evolved and when we were able to interact more with the webpages (Javascript, PHP, CSS), one could also click on a dropdown menu and check out the price list of the pizzeria which might change seasonally, and of course several advertisement banners the show information about the baseball game happening nearby. One was also able to give feedback on the website for other visitors to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to today, with the evolution of the so called So-Lo-Mo (for &lt;em&gt;Social&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Location&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Mobile&lt;/em&gt;), we could search for pizzerias in a 5 km radius around 75014. And we do not even do it on Bing or Google, rather on a specific application like Yelp. Besides the list of pizzerias around 75014 (&lt;em&gt;location&lt;/em&gt;), the app would also show us what different people liked in the pizzeria and their opinion (&lt;em&gt;social&lt;/em&gt;). Further we do not need to search for a cyber-cafe or a dial-up network in the hotel room. We can use this application from a cellular phone (&lt;em&gt;mobile&lt;/em&gt;) which has a GPS that allows us to pin-point our location on a map in case we get lost looking for the pizzeria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From searching on one single generic search page, we have moved on to specific apps that provide specific search information. If we want to know how good is a movie, rather than asking Google, we go and check the rating for the movie in IMDB. If we want to watch an awesome movie starring Margot Robbie, you search in Netflix for movies Margot Robbie stars in and pick one. If you want to look for your school friend whom you lost touch with, you search for him in Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dotkay/tmp/main/misc/bundling_unbundling_of_search.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the unbundled search started becoming more and more popular in the western world, in Asia the popular WeChat app started bundling it. More than calling it bundling, it severed as a gateway to searching many specialized goods and services from within the main search app. Many of these services (called MiniProgram) can be accessed only from within the WeChat app. One could think of WeChat as a mobile operating system within an app. All you want from a mobile operating system is a bunch of useful apps that serve your needs (unlike desktop operating system that has somewhat different set of characteristics) and WeChat provides exactly that. Lately, Facebook is trying to bundle more services (search, shopping, payment, etc.) into one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes a great search experience? Everything bundled in one - which makes it simple to search or is it better to have specialized, standalone search applications - less clutter, more refined for what we are looking for? Many top product companies are confused about this very question. The answer is not going to be simple. No one method will ever become the dominant option and so many companies need to evaluate the markets where they want to grow or maintain dominance in order to make this decision. In a future post, we will debate the impact of the different choices on search advertising.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      
        <category term="search" />
      
        <category term="internet" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">Over the last couple of decades, internet search has evolved a lot. This evolution has several facets - on one hand technology changes like Web 2.0, semantic web, richer media, etc., and on the other hand going from generic to specific - or unbundling and bundling of search. In the early days of search engines, one would search every generic thing on the search engine application. If we want to see if there are good Pizzerias near our hotel during a trip to Paris, we would look for pizzerias in Paris and whichever fancy restaurant had made an effort to create a website (a static one) might show up. As technologies evolved and when we were able to interact more with the webpages (Javascript, PHP, CSS), one could also click on a dropdown menu and check out the price list of the pizzeria which might change seasonally, and of course several advertisement banners the show information about the baseball game happening nearby. One was also able to give feedback on the website for other visitors to see. Fast forward to today, with the evolution of the so called So-Lo-Mo (for Social, Location, Mobile), we could search for pizzerias in a 5 km radius around 75014. And we do not even do it on Bing or Google, rather on a specific application like Yelp. Besides the list of pizzerias around 75014 (location), the app would also show us what different people liked in the pizzeria and their opinion (social). Further we do not need to search for a cyber-cafe or a dial-up network in the hotel room. We can use this application from a cellular phone (mobile) which has a GPS that allows us to pin-point our location on a map in case we get lost looking for the pizzeria. From searching on one single generic search page, we have moved on to specific apps that provide specific search information. If we want to know how good is a movie, rather than asking Google, we go and check the rating for the movie in IMDB. If we want to watch an awesome movie starring Margot Robbie, you search in Netflix for movies Margot Robbie stars in and pick one. If you want to look for your school friend whom you lost touch with, you search for him in Facebook. While the unbundled search started becoming more and more popular in the western world, in Asia the popular WeChat app started bundling it. More than calling it bundling, it severed as a gateway to searching many specialized goods and services from within the main search app. Many of these services (called MiniProgram) can be accessed only from within the WeChat app. One could think of WeChat as a mobile operating system within an app. All you want from a mobile operating system is a bunch of useful apps that serve your needs (unlike desktop operating system that has somewhat different set of characteristics) and WeChat provides exactly that. Lately, Facebook is trying to bundle more services (search, shopping, payment, etc.) into one. What makes a great search experience? Everything bundled in one - which makes it simple to search or is it better to have specialized, standalone search applications - less clutter, more refined for what we are looking for? Many top product companies are confused about this very question. The answer is not going to be simple. No one method will ever become the dominant option and so many companies need to evaluate the markets where they want to grow or maintain dominance in order to make this decision. In a future post, we will debate the impact of the different choices on search advertising.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">LinkedIn’s Business →</title>
      
      <link href="https://dotkay.github.io/2019/12/01/linkedin-business/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="LinkedIn's Business" />
      <published>2019-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://dotkay.github.io/2019/12/01/linkedin-business</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://dotkay.github.io/2019/12/01/linkedin-business/">&lt;p&gt;Lately, I have been reading about several businesses and trying to understand their product offerings, value proposition of the products, business model and how they came to be. With a natural inclination for technology products and a curiosity about startups and business models, this has been an enjoyable learning experience and I am hoping to share a lot of my learning through this medium. Let’s start with LinkedIn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LinkedIn’s Vision&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Create economic opportunity for every member of the global workforce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;I liked the simple and clear vision statement but was wondering why it mentions only &lt;em&gt;economic opportunity&lt;/em&gt; while LinkedIn’s products offer much more or could it be the case that all the benefits the products offer can be tied to economic opportunity? I started researching about what this term &lt;em&gt;economic opportunity&lt;/em&gt; entails and found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quora.com/How-are-economic-opportunities-defined&quot;&gt;this answer&lt;/a&gt; in Quora:&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When somebody is willing to pay you money for doing something that you are willing and able to do, that is an “economic opportunity”. It can be a small business idea or a job.If you can produce a product or provide a service that people are willing to pay for, that is a small business opportunity. If you have an ability or skill that an employer needs, that is a job opportunity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Basically, an economic opportunity is the chance to do work that somebody is willing to pay you for. You don’t have to “like” the work. You just have to be able to competently do it. If you like your work, all the better for you. But we work to earn money that is paid by other people. The work we do is for other people’s benefit. The money they pay us is for our benefit. It is a reciprocal pay-earn, demand-supply economic relationship. They pay us money for supplying them what they want.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, however, feel that LinkedIn also provides knowledge opportunity (learning), business/marketing opportunity (sales leads) and career opportunity (jobs for professionals) and talent development (hiring solutions for recruiters) opportunity, etc. There might be some or some aspects of these on which you cannot really put a dollar value on in order for them to be called an &lt;em&gt;economic opportunity&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LinkedIn’s Mission&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The mission of LinkedIn is simple: connect the world’s professionals to make them more productive and successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, a short and crisp mission statement. But, again I believe that the main benefit is making professionals more skilled, equipped, informed, etc., rather than just productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LinkedIn’s Products&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LinkedIn to many is just a networking site for professionals. But once you look at the suite of products it is much more than that. LinkedIn’s products are organized under four themes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Market&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sell&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The various products under each of these themes are shown below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/products/linkedin_products.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;LinkedIn's Products&quot; class=&quot;img=responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to categorize each of the products into &lt;em&gt;advertisement-based&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;subscription-based&lt;/em&gt; one as some of them overlap both business models. The &lt;em&gt;HIRE&lt;/em&gt; theme is mainly for human resources professionals to track, follow, and manage recruiting pipeline for their organizations. I believe this could be one of the most active products (along with learning) on the platform. The &lt;em&gt;MARKET&lt;/em&gt; theme helps in setting up marketing campaigns, reach out to potential resources for marketing purposes, set up custom pages, and serve advertisements on the pages and possibly through emails. Although it sounds like a lot of features, I believe they would have a very stiff competition from the likes of Google and Facebook. Although the advertisements would be more relevant to hiring and professional marketing, the eyeballs on these wouldn’t be as much as on Google search and Facebook feeds. However, with the volume of professionals in the network, hiring ads would get the best reach on this platform. The &lt;em&gt;SELL&lt;/em&gt; theme sounds like a specialized Salesforce platform.  The &lt;em&gt;LEARN&lt;/em&gt; theme is an upcoming Coursera. Although it may not offer a wide variety of specializations for now, with data from the &lt;em&gt;HIRE&lt;/em&gt; theme, it would be a more powerful medium for specialized skill development targeted at specific job roles in specific industries. We need to wait and watch how well Microsoft uses the data from one to better the offerings of another. Although LinkedIn membership is free, there is also a premium subscription which could be considered as a separate product in itself (creating significant revenue) and it is needed to use several of the other products, for example InMail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LinkedIn’s business&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;LinkedIn has become a significant business unit of Microsoft. According to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessofapps.com/data/linkedin-statistics/&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the 2019 fiscal year, LinkedIn brought in $6.8 billion worth of revenue, contributing to $38.1 billion of commercial cloud revenue for Microsoft, which in turn made up part of $126 billion total revenue.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further the numbers below from Microsoft’s earnings and LinkedIn newsroom validate the importance of LinkedIn and its potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/products/linkedin_fy20_q1.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;LinkedIn FY20 Q1&quot; class=&quot;img=responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/products/linkedin_stats.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;LinkedIn impact&quot; class=&quot;img=responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LinkedIn’s Opportunity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/products/linkedin_worldwide.png&quot; alt=&quot;LinkedIn Stats&quot; class=&quot;img=responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that shows the opportunity for LinkedIn. Along with the above, GitHub - the world’s largest software development platform or the playground for developers was snapped up by Microsoft. This indicates a very huge potential. The data from &lt;em&gt;HIRE&lt;/em&gt; theme above combined with &lt;em&gt;LEARN&lt;/em&gt; theme and fueled by GitHub platform is a wonderful growth opportunity. GitHub + LinkedIn for developers would be Instagram for fashionistas and for businesses and recruiters this would be the Instagram for fashion brands seeking ambassadors and influencers. Probably some day very soon let me write about the opportunity for data science and AI in stitching all the above products together as one awesome fabric.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thats all for now!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      
        <category term="technology" />
      
        <category term="products" />
      
        <category term="business" />
      
        <category term="LinkedIn" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">Lately, I have been reading about several businesses and trying to understand their product offerings, value proposition of the products, business model and how they came to be. With a natural inclination for technology products and a curiosity about startups and business models, this has been an enjoyable learning experience and I am hoping to share a lot of my learning through this medium. Let’s start with LinkedIn. LinkedIn’s Vision Create economic opportunity for every member of the global workforce. I liked the simple and clear vision statement but was wondering why it mentions only economic opportunity while LinkedIn’s products offer much more or could it be the case that all the benefits the products offer can be tied to economic opportunity? I started researching about what this term economic opportunity entails and found this answer in Quora: When somebody is willing to pay you money for doing something that you are willing and able to do, that is an “economic opportunity”. It can be a small business idea or a job.If you can produce a product or provide a service that people are willing to pay for, that is a small business opportunity. If you have an ability or skill that an employer needs, that is a job opportunity. Basically, an economic opportunity is the chance to do work that somebody is willing to pay you for. You don’t have to “like” the work. You just have to be able to competently do it. If you like your work, all the better for you. But we work to earn money that is paid by other people. The work we do is for other people’s benefit. The money they pay us is for our benefit. It is a reciprocal pay-earn, demand-supply economic relationship. They pay us money for supplying them what they want. I, however, feel that LinkedIn also provides knowledge opportunity (learning), business/marketing opportunity (sales leads) and career opportunity (jobs for professionals) and talent development (hiring solutions for recruiters) opportunity, etc. There might be some or some aspects of these on which you cannot really put a dollar value on in order for them to be called an economic opportunity. LinkedIn’s Mission The mission of LinkedIn is simple: connect the world’s professionals to make them more productive and successful. Again, a short and crisp mission statement. But, again I believe that the main benefit is making professionals more skilled, equipped, informed, etc., rather than just productive. LinkedIn’s Products LinkedIn to many is just a networking site for professionals. But once you look at the suite of products it is much more than that. LinkedIn’s products are organized under four themes: Hire Market Sell Learn The various products under each of these themes are shown below: It is difficult to categorize each of the products into advertisement-based or subscription-based one as some of them overlap both business models. The HIRE theme is mainly for human resources professionals to track, follow, and manage recruiting pipeline for their organizations. I believe this could be one of the most active products (along with learning) on the platform. The MARKET theme helps in setting up marketing campaigns, reach out to potential resources for marketing purposes, set up custom pages, and serve advertisements on the pages and possibly through emails. Although it sounds like a lot of features, I believe they would have a very stiff competition from the likes of Google and Facebook. Although the advertisements would be more relevant to hiring and professional marketing, the eyeballs on these wouldn’t be as much as on Google search and Facebook feeds. However, with the volume of professionals in the network, hiring ads would get the best reach on this platform. The SELL theme sounds like a specialized Salesforce platform. The LEARN theme is an upcoming Coursera. Although it may not offer a wide variety of specializations for now, with data from the HIRE theme, it would be a more powerful medium for specialized skill development targeted at specific job roles in specific industries. We need to wait and watch how well Microsoft uses the data from one to better the offerings of another. Although LinkedIn membership is free, there is also a premium subscription which could be considered as a separate product in itself (creating significant revenue) and it is needed to use several of the other products, for example InMail. LinkedIn’s business LinkedIn has become a significant business unit of Microsoft. According to a source In the 2019 fiscal year, LinkedIn brought in $6.8 billion worth of revenue, contributing to $38.1 billion of commercial cloud revenue for Microsoft, which in turn made up part of $126 billion total revenue. Further the numbers below from Microsoft’s earnings and LinkedIn newsroom validate the importance of LinkedIn and its potential. LinkedIn’s Opportunity And that shows the opportunity for LinkedIn. Along with the above, GitHub - the world’s largest software development platform or the playground for developers was snapped up by Microsoft. This indicates a very huge potential. The data from HIRE theme above combined with LEARN theme and fueled by GitHub platform is a wonderful growth opportunity. GitHub + LinkedIn for developers would be Instagram for fashionistas and for businesses and recruiters this would be the Instagram for fashion brands seeking ambassadors and influencers. Probably some day very soon let me write about the opportunity for data science and AI in stitching all the above products together as one awesome fabric. Thats all for now!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
</feed>
